<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Case and cure of persons excommunicated according to the present law of England in two parts : I. the nature of excommunication, as founded in Holy Writ : the persons intrusted with that power, the objects of that censure and the method prescribed by God for it : the corruptions of it in times of popery, with the acts of the popish clergy, to fortify it with under these corruptions : the several writs of common law, and the statute laws made in those times, and still in force : to restrain the abuse of this censure, and to deliver the subjects from the oppression of it : II. the mischievous consequents of excommunication as the law now stands at present in England : with some friendly advice to persons pursued in inferior ecclesiatical courts by malicious promoters : both in order to their avoiding excommunication, or delivering themselves from prisons, if imprisoned because they have stood excommunicated fourty days.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35587</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4831</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13201356</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13201356</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98452</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35587)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98452)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 449:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Case and cure of persons excommunicated according to the present law of England in two parts : I. the nature of excommunication, as founded in Holy Writ : the persons intrusted with that power, the objects of that censure and the method prescribed by God for it : the corruptions of it in times of popery, with the acts of the popish clergy, to fortify it with under these corruptions : the several writs of common law, and the statute laws made in those times, and still in force : to restrain the abuse of this censure, and to deliver the subjects from the oppression of it : II. the mischievous consequents of excommunication as the law now stands at present in England : with some friendly advice to persons pursued in inferior ecclesiatical courts by malicious promoters : both in order to their avoiding excommunication, or delivering themselves from prisons, if imprisoned because they have stood excommunicated fourty days.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. R. sold by Richard Janeway,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Excommunication --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ecclesiastical law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98452:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98452:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE and CURE OF <hi>Perſons Excommunicated</hi> According to The preſent Law of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Two Parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>The nature of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> as founded in Holy Writ; the Perſons intruſted with that Power; the Objects of that Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the Method preſcribed by God for it.</item>
               <item>The Corruptions of it in times of <hi>Popery,</hi> with the Acts of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Clergy, to fortify it with under theſe Corruptions. The ſeveral Writs of Common Law, and the Statute Laws made in thoſe times, and ſtill in force, to reſtrain the abuſe of this Cenſure, and to deliver the Subjects from the Oppreſſion of it.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>II.</head>
               <item>The <hi>Miſchievous Conſequents</hi> of Excommunication as the Law now ſtands at preſent in <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>With ſome Friendly Advice to Perſons purſued in Inferior <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts</hi> by <hi>Malicious Promoters;</hi> both in order to their <hi>avoiding Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> or <hi>delivering</hi> themſelves from <hi>Priſons,</hi> if impriſoned, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have ſtood Excommunicated Fourty days.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. R.</hi> Sold by <hi>Richard Janeway.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:98452:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98452:2"/>
            <head>PART I. <hi>The</hi> Caſe <hi>and</hi> Cure <hi>of Perſons Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated according to the preſent Law of</hi> England.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Foundation of Excommunication, both in Reaſon, and from Scripture, both of the Old and New Teſtament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xcommunication,</hi> being the <hi>Separation of a Perſon from the Communion of the Church,</hi> at leaſt in ſome <hi>Ordinances,</hi> ſeems to be founded in the <hi>Law of Reaſon</hi> as well as in <hi>Holy Writ;</hi> for it is very irrational to imagine, that any <hi>Political Body,</hi> ſhould be left without a Power, to purge it ſelf from ſuch <hi>Members of it,</hi> as are unfit for <hi>Communion with it.</hi> And as the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Order</hi> never left any <hi>Kingdom, or Commonwealth,</hi> without a Power to <hi>make</hi> and <hi>execute,</hi> or at leaſt, to execute ſuch Laws as were neceſſary for its <hi>Preſervation:</hi> So it is moſt of all unreaſonable to imagine, That that Body, whereof Chriſt is the <hi>Head,</hi> ſhould not be cloathed with Authority ſufficient to free it ſelf from <hi>diſorderly Members.</hi> God, who himſelf inſtituted all the Laws of the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> did not leave that Church without a Power to keep their Communion <hi>pure and holy.</hi> Hence we ſhall find that Penalty, — <hi>He ſhall be cut off from his People,</hi> — ſo often annexed to thoſe Laws, which doubtleſs is not to be underſtood of <hi>Eternal Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> for it is unreaſonable to imagine, that the Child of eight days old, ſhould be eternally condemned for the Parents neglect to circumciſe it; <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14. Nor of <hi>Corporal Puniſhments alone;</hi> for tho God was about
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98452:3"/>to have killed <hi>Moſes,</hi> for not <hi>circumciſing his Child,</hi> yet we read of no danger the <hi>Child</hi> was in; but the Phraſe is certainly to be underſtood of a <hi>penal, judicial Separation of the Perſon from the viſible Communion of the Church.</hi> And that ſome ſuch thing was in practice amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> appears in their moſt corrupt times, both by their caſting one out of the <hi>Synagogue in Chriſt's time,</hi> whom he received, and by his <hi>Prediction</hi> to his Diſciples, that the <hi>Jews</hi> would for their Confeſſion of him, <hi>turn them out of the Synagogues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the Reformation, and the Settlement of the <hi>Chriſtian Church;</hi> Chriſt is ſuppoſed to have clothed his Church with ſuch a Power: <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. <hi>And I will give unto thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven; and whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven, and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven.</hi> The ſame Power he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to more of his Diſciples: <hi>John</hi> 20.23. <hi>Whoſoever Sins ye remit, they are remitted, and whoſoever Sins ye retain, they are retained.</hi> Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſeemeth more particularly to direct in the Caſe: <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Moreover, if thy Brother ſhall treſpaſs againſt thee, go, and tell him his Fault betwixt thee and him alone: if he ſhall hear thee, thou haſt gained thy Brother. But if he will not hear thee, then take with thee one or two more, that in the mouth of two or three Witneſſes every Word may be eſtabliſhed: And if he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to hear them, tell it the Church: if he neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen, and a Publican. Verily, I ſay unto you, whatſoever you ſhall bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven, and whatſoever you ſhall looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven.</hi> More than this we find not in our Saviour's Directions, given by himſelf. But he, <hi>aſcending up on high, gave Gifts unto Men, Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors and Teachers. Apoſtles</hi> to plant Churches, and to put them in order, revealing his. Will unto them for their Order and Government; <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> for the ordinary <hi>Government of them,</hi> by putting the <hi>Laws</hi> in Execution, which Chriſt perſonally gave, or which the Apoſtles gave for the order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Government of them: we find the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> more fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing us, as to this Ordinance of Excommunication; we have an eminent Inſtance, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. A Perſon that was a Member of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> had taken his <hi>Father's Wife,</hi> the Apoſtles Judgment concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, is declared, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>In the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, when ye are gathered together, and my Spirit, with the Power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to deliver ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e unto Satan, for the Deſtruction of the Fleſh, that the Spirit may be ſaved in the day of our Lord Jeſus.</hi> That Phraſe of <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring unto Satan,</hi> is again mentioned, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. of whom is <hi>Hymeneus,</hi> and <hi>Alexander, whom I have delivered unto Satan, that they may learn not to blaſpheme.</hi> Moſt agree, that the Apoſtle in theſe Texts, by <hi>delivering
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98452:3"/>to Satan,</hi> and underſtands <hi>Excommunication,</hi> why, he expreſſeth it by the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>delivering up to Satan,</hi> is not ſo uniformly agreed: Some think that Excommunicated Perſons were in theſe Times: <hi>corporally vexed by Satan.</hi> I could never ſee it well proved, at leaſt that it was ordinarily done: tho God might make ſome ſuch remarkable Inſtances of his Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. There is a ſenſe in the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> which pleaſeth me much better <hi>which</hi> is by the Apoſtle, called, <hi>The God of the World;</hi> as the <hi>Church</hi> is God's Houſe, ſo Men out of the <hi>Church,</hi> are in <hi>Satan's Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories,</hi> and under his <hi>Government,</hi> and this certainly is the meaning of that Phraſe. The Apoſtle delivered up <hi>Hymen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> who had put away <hi>Faith</hi> and a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> to the <hi>World,</hi> that is, <hi>Shut them out of the Communion of God's Houſe,</hi> which is the Church, and <hi>left them to the World,</hi> and this comporteth with our Saviour's Inſtitution. <hi>Let him be to them as an Heathen, and as a Publican:</hi> From which alſo appeareth, that Perſons under that Sentence might according to the Will of God, be admitted to ſuch Ordinances as <hi>Heathens</hi> might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to, who might be <hi>preached</hi> to, and <hi>prayed</hi> for: Yea the <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated</hi> Perſon, was in ſomething a better Condition than a meer <hi>Pagan,</hi> for the Church was under an Obligation to <hi>admoniſh him</hi> as one that had been <hi>a Brother;</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6, 14. he had given command, <hi>That if any Brother did walk diſorderly, they ſhould withdraw themſelves from him:</hi> ver. 14. they ſhould <hi>note him, and have no company with him, that he might be aſhamed;</hi> yet <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>Count him not as an Enemy, but admoniſh him as a Brother.</hi> Yet in ſome reſpects it appeareth to be the will of God, that an <hi>Excommunicated Perſon ſhould be treated worſe than an Heathen.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.9, 10. <hi>I wrote you an Epiſtle</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>not to company with Fornicators, Yet not altogether with the Fornicators of this World, or with the Covetous, or with Extortioners, or Idolaters, for then muſt you needs go out of the World.</hi> Ver. 11. <hi>But now I have written to you, not to keep Company, if any Man that is called a Brother, be a Fornicator, or Covetous, or an Idolater, or Railer, or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner, with ſuch a one no not to eat.</hi> By which it appeareth, that ſuch Perſons as are here ſpecified, were to be withdrawn from, and to that degree, that Men ſhould rather have an Intimacy of Communion with Heathens, than with them. What further Direction we have in this Caſe, is in the Epiſtles to <hi>Titu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> Tit. 3.10. <hi>A Man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond Admonition, reject.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.2. <hi>Men ſhall be lovers of their own ſelves, Covetous, Boaſters, Proud, Blaſphemers, diſobedient to Parents, unthankful, unholy, without natural Affection, Truce-breakers, incontinent, fierce, Deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of that which is good, Traitors, Heady-minded, Lovers of Pleaſures more that Lovers of God. Having a Form of Godlineſs, and denying the Power
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98452:4"/>thereof: from ſuch turn away.</hi> Rom. 16.17. <hi>Mark them which make Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions amongst you contrary to the Doctrine which you have received, and avoid them.</hi> This is the moſt of what we find in Holy Writ concerning this <hi>Inſtitution of Chriſt,</hi> both as to the Doctrine concerning it, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Practice of it, from whence may be eaſily gathered, that the Deſcription which the Canoniſts anciently gave of it, is not much amiſs; for <hi>Panormitan</hi> telleth us, That Excommunication is nothing elſe, but <hi>a Cenſure pronounced by the Canon, or the Judg Eccleſiaſtical, by which a Perſon is deprived of the Communion of the Sacraments, and ſometimes with Men.</hi> The former of which, he calleth the <hi>leſſer;</hi> the latter, the <hi>greater Excommunication.</hi> It is a more Theological Deſcription of it, to ſay, <hi>It is an Inſtitution of Chriſt for keeping the Purity of his Church, by which, ſuch as he hath authorized thereunto, have Power in ſuch order and manner, as he hath appointed, to ſeparate from the more intimate Communion of a Church in ſuch Ordinances, as may not be adminiſtred to Pagans, ſuch Perſons as Chriſt hath declared unfit for that Communion, untill they have declared their bearty Repentance for ſuch Miſcarriages.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A further Inquiry concerning the Perſons whom God intruſted with the Power of Excommunication, being one of the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven; they are proved to be Apoſtles and Paſtors of Churches, with the conſent of the Body of the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE are, for the fuller <hi>underſtanding</hi> of the Will of God in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, in the firſt place, to inquire <hi>to whom our Lord Jeſus hath truſted this Power.</hi> He tells <hi>Peter,</hi> Mat. 16.19. <hi>And I will give unto thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> A Text the <hi>Papiſts</hi> make great uſe of. But is no more than he tells all his Diſciples of, <hi>John</hi> 20.23. <hi>Whoſe ſoever Sins you remit, they are remitted to them, and whoſe ſover Sins you retain, are retained;</hi> and in the <hi>Rule</hi> he gives us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. concerning <hi>Offences</hi> not committed publickly (for ſuch Caſes there is no need of <hi>fraternal Correption,</hi> as appears, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Thoſe that ſin, rebuke before all</hi>) he commands the third time they ſhould tell the Church, and if the Offender would not <hi>hear the Church, he ſhould be as an Heathen, or a Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can.</hi> The Church can be no ſingle Perſon; nor doth he write to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Paſtors,</hi> but to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> about the <hi>inceſtuous Perſon,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. and directs them that the Act ſhould be done <hi>when they ſhould be gathered together in the Name of Chriſt.</hi> There are in Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98452:4"/>two things: <hi>The Judgment of the Cauſe,</hi> and the <hi>Pronouncing of the Sentence. The pronouncing or publiſhing of the Sentence,</hi> is a meer <hi>Miniſterial Work:</hi> yet we do not find, that it was ever done but by a <hi>Biſhop or Miniſter.</hi> But the main buſineſs is to inquire whom Chriſt (the Lord of the Church) hath betruſted with, <hi>hearing theſe Cauſes, and judging concerning them;</hi> for of his Appointment they muſt be: who hath any thing to do to turn any out of his Houſe, but either he himſelf, who is the Lord of the Houſe, or ſuch as he hath delegated thereunto? St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he had delivered up to Satan <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus.</hi> He or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth <hi>Titus</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> (or Paſtor at leaſt) of <hi>Crete,</hi> to <hi>reject an Heretick after the firſt and ſecond Admonition.</hi> He writes to the <hi>Church of</hi> Corinth, <hi>where they were gathered together, to deliver up the inceſtuous Perſon to Satan.</hi> From whence we may indeed conclude, That the Miniſter is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; but not that it was ever committed to him alone, without the conſent of the <hi>Congregation;</hi> and it is a Rule of Reaſon, <hi>Quod omnes tangit ab omnibus tangi debet;</hi> the whole Body is concerned in the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of any Member: and in vain ſhall any Officers caſt one out of Communion with the Church, with whom, yet the Church will keep Communion. Nothing appears more clear to me, than that it belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the <hi>Biſhop or Paſtor,</hi> with the <hi>whole Church,</hi> to hear ſuch Cauſes, and the <hi>Paſtor and Officers</hi> to judg of them; which being granted, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee how any Perſon can be lawfully Excommunicated by any <hi>Council,</hi> or <hi>Synod;</hi> it muſt proceed from <hi>the Church gathered together;</hi> and that the Officers of many Churches gathered together, ſhould make a Church, clothed with Authority from Chriſt, to Excommunicate, I cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand from any thing of Holy-Writ. And indeed, I take one of the firſt warpings from the Rule of Chriſt, as to this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> to have been then: For had the Cauſe been of much more weight, than the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timing of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> I cannot underſtand by what Authority (unleſs u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped) <hi>Victor</hi> could Exccommunicate the <hi>Churches of Aſia.</hi> But (to paſs this) for more than five hundred Years after Chriſt, the Churches never allowed it within the Power of any, but either of the <hi>Collective Church,</hi> or the <hi>Biſhops and Paſtors</hi> in their reſpective Churches, to hear the Cauſes of Perſons with reference to the Solemn Sentence of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> and to determin any to it. In the third <hi>Century,</hi> the Power reſted <hi>penes Seniores Eccleſiae,</hi> in the Elders of the Church, as appears from <hi>Tertullian's Apologetick;</hi> and the <hi>Denunciation</hi> of the <hi>Sentence</hi> was by a <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Presbyter;</hi> this <hi>Origen</hi> hinteth to us again and again. Thus it was in <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Time in the Caſe of <hi>Fortunatus, Foeliciſſimus Maximus,</hi> and <hi>Jevinus:</hi> and thus, if we will believe Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, <hi>Fabranus</hi> Excommunicated the <hi>Emperor Philip</hi> (tho I give little Credit to <hi>Euſebius</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98452:5"/>in that Story, believing the courſe of excommunicating Emperors of much latter Date.) In the fourth <hi>Century,</hi> we read of many Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, yet none but by <hi>Biſhops, or Paſtors.</hi> The Biſhop of <hi>Laodicea</hi> Excommunicated <hi>Apollinarius:</hi> The Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated <hi>Aris, &amp;c.</hi> Still it was the Work of <hi>Biſhops or Paſtors,</hi> and none other. Thus it was in the 5th and 6th <hi>Centuries:</hi> Nay, in the 7th <hi>Century,</hi> the Centuriators tell us, That the Power was only in <hi>Biſhops and Prieſts;</hi> but <hi>Pope Boniface</hi> had inveſted Monks with it, <hi>Anno</hi> 1518. When the Power of <hi>Excommunication</hi> came into the hands of <hi>Laicks</hi> under the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Officials,</hi> I know of no Hiſtory will inform us; but it is eaſie to be concluded, that it muſt do ſo, from the time that <hi>Biſhops</hi> claimed to themſelves the ſole Power in it, and charged themſelves with ſo many Churches, as a thouſand Eyes (tho very watchful) could not poſſibly overſee; there was a neceſſity they ſhould delegate their Power in this Cauſe to others, becauſe it was not poſſible they ſhould execute it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; nor could they delegate it to the <hi>Curates,</hi> becauſe then a ſhort time would have diſcovered to whom it did of right belong; nor could the <hi>Grandeur</hi> of <hi>Prelates</hi> have been upheld without a <hi>Court,</hi> nor the Officers of that Court have lived, with out having ſomething to do. We ſtill maintain that <hi>Biſhops</hi> alone can Excommunicate. <hi>Ordination, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> are all pretended Differences betwixt them and other Minſters of the Goſpel. The Execution of this Sentence by <hi>Officials</hi> is pretended to be but by <hi>Delegation;</hi> only why they may not alſo delegate to ſuch Officials, their Authority alſo, to <hi>preach,</hi> and <hi>baptize,</hi> and <hi>ordain Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>adminiſter the Euchariſt,</hi> as to hear the Cauſes of Perſons complained of, for Error, and Hereſy, or Leudneſs of Life, will deſerve their own Thoughts, and every ſerious and thinking Man's Enquiry. Theſe things conſidered, I cannot but be amazed, when I read what I find in Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Collection of <hi>Records,</hi> pag. 239. added to his firſt Part of the Hiſtory of our <hi>Reformation;</hi> how ſome of our great <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> in the time of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8th, in the beginning of our Reformation, delivered themſelves upon this Queſtion. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Canterbury, Hereford,</hi> St. <hi>Davids,</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Dr. <hi>Day, Coren, Leighton, Cox, Simmons,</hi> declared their Judgments contrary to Scripture, and all Antiquity, <hi>That Lay Perſons might Excommunicate, if they were appointed thereto by the Magiſtrate.</hi> So as they held, it ſeems, that Chriſt gave the Power of <hi>Excommunication to Magiſtrates,</hi> or that whether he did or no, they might take and delegate it. The Biſhops of <hi>York,</hi> and <hi>Durham,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Edgworth</hi> denied it. Three more held it was given to the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſuch as they ſhould depute unto it. But ſomething muſt be allowed to that time, when we were beginning to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98452:5"/>reform, and our greateſt Men had too great a Tincture of <hi>Popery,</hi> both as to <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's time, What the Opinion of Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and many others were, appears by that <hi>Syſteme of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Canons,</hi> which they compoſed by Commiſſion from that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince, and are to be found in the Book called <hi>Reformatio Legum Eccleſiaſticarum;</hi> where they determine,</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>That no one Perſon ſhould execute this Power, but that the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Biſhop, or ſome other lawful Judge, with a Juſtice of the Peace, and the Proper Miniſter of the Place, where the Party ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed dwelleth, or ſome other appointed by him, and two or three other Religious Miniſters ſhould meet, in whoſe Preſence, after a full Handling, and weighing the Cauſe, the Party ſhould be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>They had ſaid before, <hi>p.</hi> 161. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>That the conſent of the whole Church was to be wiſhed; but becauſe that is hard to be procured, they orainded as aforeſaid.</hi> Now what difficulty was there in obtaining the conſent of the whole Church, but the extending the Notion of a <hi>Political Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church,</hi> beyond the number of ſo many, as in one place could be gathered together, or could be under the Government of the ſame Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, out of the Cauſe of Appeals, in which Cauſes it might poſſibly be ſo extended? But I obſerve in the Determination of thoſe Great and Reverend Perſons (if the conſent of the Congregation be not neceſſary, which yet I incline much to believe) they had put in all who can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any ſuch juſt Power; <hi>viz.</hi> The Biſhop, and the Miniſter of the place; and if the other be only allowed as <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> to whom the <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Power</hi> belongs not, poſſibly that Determination was not evil. But I conclude, with the Evidence of Holy Writ, the conſent of all valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Antiquity, and from the Evidence of Reaſon, <hi>That Chriſt hath not betruſted this Church-Key with any but the Paſtor, and Officers, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the particular Church, to which the Offender doth belong,</hi> and any Excommunication decreed or executed by any other, is no more than a <hi>Civil Puniſhment,</hi> and the effect of an <hi>Humane Law,</hi> and can pretend to no <hi>Inſtitution of Chriſt,</hi> nor <hi>Authority from Apoſtolical Writings;</hi> and it were well the Name of Chriſt were left out of thoſe Sentences, which can pretend to no Authority from him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98452:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An Inquiry into thoſe Crimes for which alone according to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Rule, Excommunication ought to proceed, and be iſſued by the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe next thing we have to conſider is, the Objects of this Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, admitting it a meer <hi>Civil Puniſhment.</hi> The Objects of it muſt be determined by the Laws of Men; and the Juſtice or Injuſtice of the Execution of it upon them, muſt be determined by the Law of God, another Day. But by a Parity of Reaſon, if it be an Inſtitution of Chriſt's, the <hi>Objects of this Cenſure</hi> muſt be determined by the <hi>Law of God;</hi> and it is not in the Power of Man to make an Alteration in the Caſe; nor hath the Scripture left us without a Determination in the Caſe. Three things according to Scripture, muſt concur to make an Object of this heavy Cenſure. (1.) <hi>The Party muſt be a Sinner.</hi>— whoſe <hi>Sins you retain, are retained.</hi> (2.) <hi>Nor is every Sinner the object of it,</hi> but he muſt be, 1. Either an Heretick, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.10. One that hath <hi>made Shipwrack of the Faith.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 19. Or a <hi>ſcandalous, flagitious Sinner,</hi> ſuch as hath made <hi>Shipwrack of a good Conſcience;</hi> an <hi>Inceſtuous</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, one that is <hi>Proud, Covetous,</hi> a <hi>Boaſter,</hi> a <hi>Blaſphemer,</hi> one <hi>diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Parents, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankful, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholy, without Natural Affection, a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Breaker, a falſe Accuſer, one that is fierce, Incontinent, a Deſpiſer of ſuch as are Good, Traitors, Heady, High-minded; one who is a Lover of Pleaſures, more than a Lover of God: One that tho he may have a Form of Godlineſs, yet denieth the Power of it,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. <hi>One that obeyeth not the Word of God, that walketh diſorderly,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3.6, 14. <hi>One that is a Fornicator, an Idolater, a Drunkard, a Railer, an Extortioner,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. <hi>One that cauſeth Diviſions contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 16.17. And not only theſe, but in reaſon ſuch as ſhut a Man out of the Kingdom of God, and are equally heinous and ſcandalous as theſe; ſuch as are reckoned up by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Idolaters, Adulterers, Effeminate Perſons, ſuch as abuſe themſelves with Mankind, Theeves, Murderers, Sorcerers, profane Swearers, and Curſers;</hi> theſe are all ſcandalous Offenders, and ſo within the Precept, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. (3.) Yet neither are all theſe the Objects of this Cenſure, unleſs they be <hi>Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, Contumacious, and Incorrigible.</hi> An <hi>Heretick</hi> is not to be avoided till after the <hi>firſt and ſecond Admonition,</hi> Tit. 3.10. Nor an <hi>Offender,</hi> till after that he hath refuſed to <hi>hear the Church,</hi> Mat. 18.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98452:6"/>
               <p> Conformable to this was the general Judgment of the Churches of God, for more than a thouſand Years after Chriſt, as might be made appear from infinite Quotations, out of the Ancients, and out of the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> which ſteadily determineth, That none but <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and ſuch as are guilty of <hi>Mortal Sins,</hi> and Contumacious in them, are to be Excommunicated.</p>
               <p>It is a moſt unreaſonable thing to think, that it is the Will of God that any ſhould be Excommunicated for what is no Sin. Chriſt never willed the cutting off true Members from his Body. And it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as unreaſonable to imagine, that it is the will of Chriſt, <hi>who hath Compaſſion on the Ignorant, and thoſe who are out of the Way,</hi> and who hath declared his readineſs to receive <hi>repenting Sinners,</hi> ſhould have willed the cutting off of thoſe from the Communion of his Church, who are not <hi>Contumacious.</hi> But this is granted on all hands, that none (be they never ſo great Tranſgreſſors) unleſs <hi>Contumacious,</hi> ſhould be the Objects of this Cenſure, at leaſt what they call the greater <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication;</hi> for the <hi>Separation</hi> of ſome open notorious Tranſgreſſors, from Communion in ſome Ordinances, being under the Church's <hi>Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> it cannot indeed properly be called <hi>Excommunication.</hi> But when a Perſon is to be judged <hi>Contumacious,</hi> is the great Queſtion. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> making the Laws and Decrees of their Church, equal, if not ſuperiour, to the Laws of God, make all Diſobedience to their <hi>Canons,</hi> perſiſted, in to be Contumacy. And in abuſe of that Text, Matth. 18. <hi>If he will not hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen and a Publican,</hi> determine all Perſons contumacious who will not hear thoſe whom they call the Church. 1. <hi>Either commanding them to appear at their Conſiſtories.</hi> 2. <hi>Or tho appearing, if they will not within ſuch a time as they ſet, do what in thoſe Courts they think fit to enjoyn them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But indeed, that Contumacy which renders any, according to the Will of God, the Objects of this Cenſure, muſt be a <hi>Contumacy</hi> againſt the Commands of Chriſt. If indeed any Perſon hath done any thing, for which according to the Will of God he is cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by the Church, and they ſend for him, and he will not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to anſwer and juſtify himſelf: Or, if they command him to do, what Chriſt hath in his Goſppel commanded them to do, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth after ſeveral Admonitions to do it, he may be judged <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious;</hi> but other Contumacy the Scripture knoweth not; nor can any Perſon by the Law of the Goſpel be judged a Perſon fit to be Excommunicated, but one who hath been a <hi>ſcandalous Sinner,</hi> who being ſent for by the Church, of which he is a Member, refuſeth to come at them: or coming to them, being required to do what is the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98452:7"/>will of Chriſt, peremptorily refuſeth to yield Obedience, but will ſtill go on in his ſinful Courſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Divine Order, Method and Manner, to be proceeded in, with Reference to Excommunication.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>There is yet one thing more to be conſidered, and that is the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> of the <hi>Execution</hi> of this <hi>Sentence,</hi> according to the Will of God. Whoſo conſidereth it as an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> an Action done <hi>in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>with the Power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it in 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5.4.) will eaſily conclude, it ought to be done with all the <hi>Seriouſneſs and Gravity</hi> imaginable, and as is uſually ſaid in our <hi>Officials Sentences,</hi> (how truly God knoweth) <hi>Chriſti nomine prius invocato,</hi> after a firſt calling upon the Name of Chriſt. The Name and Power of Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be trifled with, without <hi>Profanation</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and an high degree of taking the Name of God in vain, which is a Crime that whoſoever preſumeth to incur, ſhall not be held guiltleſs, as we are aſſured in the third Commandment. Again, whoſo conſidereth it as an <hi>Action,</hi> by which <hi>Mens Sins are retained,</hi> and by which a Perſon is caſt out of God's <hi>ſpecial Providence,</hi> and put <hi>into the condition of an Heathen and a Publican,</hi> and debarred of the greateſt Priviledges of the Goſpel, <hi>viz. the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Sacrament,</hi> and the <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> if he be a Perſon who hath any thing of the Fear of God before his Eyes, or any thing of <hi>brotherly Love,</hi> and Compaſſion toward Souls in his Heart, will eaſily conclude, it is a thing ought not to be done <hi>paſſionately, raſhly, or ſuddenly,</hi> but upon mature Deliberation, after grave Admonitions, and patient waiting for the due effect of them. And as the very Nature of the thing thus far inſtructeth any Men of Common Senſe and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities, ſo that no other manner of performing this can be expected from any, but ſuch as in their ordinary Diſcourſe are ſo uſed to throw out, <hi>The Divel take you,</hi> that they cannot forbear it in their moſt <hi>ſolemne Actions;</hi> ſo God hath ſufficiently inſtructed us in his Will as to this thing. The <hi>ſecret Sinner</hi> muſt have a <hi>private</hi> and <hi>Fraternal Correption,</hi> before the Church hear of his Crime, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>The Heretick muſt not be rejected till after a firſt and ſecond Admonition,</hi> Tit. 3.10. and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he that hath commanded us, <hi>In meekneſs to inſtruct thoſe that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them Repentance to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98452:7"/>of the Truth: And that they may recover themſelves out of the Snare of the Divel, who are taken captive by him at his will,</hi> 2 Tim 2.26. And again, <hi>If a Man be overtaken with a Fault, reſtore ſuch a one in the Spirit of Meekneſs, conſidering our ſelves, leſt we alſo be tempted,</hi> Gal. 6.1. never intended that Men ſhould be delivered up to the Devil, caſt out of the Communion of the Saints, in haſte. And indeed this is ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent a piece of the Will of God, ſo conſonant to Humane Reaſon, that not only all Divines, as well Ancient as Modern, have agreed it; but the very <hi>Canon Law</hi> it ſelf in ſeveral places determines it, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it a grievous Sin for any <hi>Biſhop or Prieſt</hi> to proceed to this Sentence, without a leiſurable and full hearing of the Cauſe. And I remember the Inſtance of God himſelf is brought in, reſolving to go down and ſee if the Merits of the Men of <hi>Sodom</hi> were according to the cry come up; and as to the deliberate proceeding of the Judge, as in the hearing, and proof of the Cauſe, ſo in the denouncing the Sentence, it ſpeaketh ſo much as one would think more were needleſs to be ſaid.</p>
               <p>So as the haſty thundering out of Excommunications, which we ſee in our Days, is ſo far from deriving any Repute or Authority from <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> that it cannot ſo much as derive from the Popiſh <hi>Canon Law.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Original of thoſe Corruptions which have been, or are found, in the Church, as to Excommunications.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>SInce the <hi>Pope</hi> claimed to himſelf the Title of the <hi>Head of the Viſible Church,</hi> all Eccleſiaſtical Power hath been pretended to derive from him; who grants it, or ſuch part of it, as he pleaſeth, to <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Arch-deacons,</hi> &amp;c. with a Power alſo to them to delegate it unto others. Thoſe who are broken off from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet will have <hi>National</hi> and <hi>Dioceſan Churches,</hi> muſt make <hi>Biſhops</hi> the <hi>Spiritual Heads</hi> of them, clothed with immediate Power from Chriſt, to influence their ſeveral Churches, and to deal out God's Ordinances unto them. To keep my ſelf to that particular Ordinance which is the Subject of my Diſcourſe. The <hi>Canon Law</hi> of old determined, That <hi>Laymen being licenſed from the Pope</hi> (the Vicar of Chriſt) <hi>might excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate,</hi> and even <hi>Biſhops</hi> might not, in ſome particular Cauſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to his Holineſs. Since <hi>Biſhops</hi> extended their <hi>Dioceſes</hi> beyond the reach of their own Eye, and the poſſibility of their own Perſonal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98452:8"/>Care, there was a neceſſity alſo of their <hi>delegating</hi> their Power as to Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. Whether this neceſſity did not ariſe from their own Error in taking Charges, which according to the Divine Rule they could not diſcharge, I leave to others to inquire; as alſo by what Authority any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Officer</hi> can depute another, to uſe the key of Diſcipline com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, more than the <hi>Key of Knowledg, or the Adminiſtration of Sacraments.</hi> Suppoſing them to have a Power to delegate, they muſt either delegate it to <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>Lay-men.</hi> To have deputed only Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of particular Congregations, had been both very <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> and <hi>dangerous:</hi> unreaſonable, that a Miniſter of a particular Congregation, ſhould have a Power to excommunicate the Members of another; for the <hi>Biſhop</hi> could not make him <hi>Paſtor of the whole Dioceſe:</hi> And dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous too to the <hi>Epiſcopal Function,</hi> leſt People ſhould have been nurſed up in an Opinion, that the Miniſter did it by his own Power, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately derived from Chriſt, and ſo there had been no need of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> for Juriſdiction. Thus when one abſurdity is granted, an hundred follow. Upon this point I will only add the Teſtimony of Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> (ſometimes <hi>Lord Chancellour</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) not ſo much for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as for the Reaſon of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Two things there are (ſaith he) in our Epiſcopal Government in which I was never ſatisfied. 1. <hi>The ſingle Exerciſe of their Authority.</hi> 2. <hi>Their Deputation of it. After he had ſpoken fully to the firſt, he comes to the latter.</hi> Our <hi>Biſhops</hi> (ſaith he) exerciſe their Juriſdiction by Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, Commiſſaries, Officials, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We ſee that according to the Laws of all Nations throughout the World, Offices which require Skill and Truſt, are not executed by Deputation, unleſs it be ſo expreſſed in the Original Commiſſion, and in that caſe it is lawful. No Judg in any Court ever ſubſtituted a Deputy. The Biſhop is a Judg; and that in Matters of an higher Nature; how cometh he to ſubſtitute ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when as all Truſt is perſonal, and inherent in the Perſon tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and cannot be transferred to another? Certainly as to this, <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> It is (ſaith he) probable, that when Biſhops gave themſelves too much to the Pomp of this World, and in Kingdoms became Peers, and Councellours to Princes, they delegated their Juriſdiction, which was proper to them, as a thing beneath their Greatneſs, and like Kings and Count-Palatines would have Councellours and Judges under them.</q> That learned Author ſpeaks a great deal more in this Cauſe. Nor hath any conſciencious, learned Man that I know, defended this Power of hearing and judging Cauſes in order to Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, in the hands of any, ſave only ſuch as have been <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98452:8"/>of the Goſpel,</hi> or the whole Church, or the <hi>Lawfulneſs of Deputations</hi> in the Caſe. It was firſt practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that in lateſt, and moſt corrupt Ages.</p>
               <p>From the ſame Authors, are derived <hi>Excommunications</hi> for light and trivial things, a thing condemned by all <hi>Ancient Councils,</hi> and up and down in the <hi>Canon-Law,</hi> which forbiddeth all <hi>Excommunications,</hi> unleſs for <hi>Hereſy,</hi> or for ſome <hi>Mortal Sin.</hi> But we muſt know to what an heighth of Power the Advocates for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had cryed up that Church: That it was impoſſible any could be guilty of a more <hi>Mortal Sin,</hi> than <hi>not coming,</hi> when any Officers of that Church ſaid, <hi>Come;</hi> or <hi>not going,</hi> when they ſaid, <hi>Go;</hi> or not <hi>doing this</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> when they ſaid, <hi>Do it.</hi> Hence it came to paſs, that when as originally the <hi>Church</hi> had nothing to do to ſend for any as a <hi>Criminal,</hi> but he that was accuſed as ſuch, for ſome Crime, for which, according to the Law of God, he was (if found guilty) to be excommunicated, in which Caſe indeed, his non-appearance might be interpreted a Confeſſion of the Guilt, and a Contumacy in it. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> having from the Favour of Princes, got for their <hi>Biſhops</hi> the Cogniſance of a Multitude of temporal Cauſes, and conſequently Authority to ſummon People to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and to decree in the Cauſe; their not appearing to ſuch Summons, or not obeying ſuch Decrees, was alſo judged a <hi>Contumacy to the Church,</hi> and the Crime deſerving Excommunication, than which a greater Abuſe cannot eaſily be imagined. And it is no wonder, that after that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication came to be the Work of thoſe, who had no place in the Church of Chriſt, as to matters of Judgment, and alſo came to be thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred out upon every light occaſion, and ſo had loſt all the repute of a Divine Inſtitution, thence it came as ſlightly to be managed or denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, all the Gravity and Seriouſneſs of the Adminiſtration was loſt. The leiſurable Admonitions given, with the Interpoſition of many Days and Months, were turned to the ſlighty ſaying thrice in a breath, <hi>I admoniſh you the firſt time, I admoniſh you the ſecond time, I admoniſh you the third time.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98452:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Reaſon of the contempt of Excommunications</hi> frome hence. The Arts <hi>of the Papiſts</hi> to ſtrengthen it with other Penalties, from <hi>Canon, and Common, and Statute Laws: The Magiſtrates diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Errors, even in Popiſh Times, reſtraining them again by ſeveral Writs of Prohibition, and Superſedeas, and Attachments, and the Writ</hi> de Cautione admittenda.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BY this time <hi>Excommunication,</hi> which rightly adminiſtred, was the moſt formidable Sentence that could be pronounced in any Court under Heaven; at once depriving the Perſon of that <hi>ſpecial Providence</hi> of God peculiar to his Church, and of the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> and of the hope of the <hi>Pardon of Sins without a Repentance</hi> teſtified; became a contemptible thing in the Eyes of the People; and tho a great while they ſtudied by their Canon Laws to uphold its Authority, denying the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated Perſons <hi>Burial</hi> in <hi>Church-yards,</hi> a <hi>Power to make a Will,</hi> and ſuch other things as were within their Power, which things by the <hi>Popes</hi> long Uſurpations, became a kind of <hi>Common Law</hi> in <hi>Nations</hi> ſubju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated to that Religion; yet they found all this too little to uphold the Authority of an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, whoſe Virtue themſelves had extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by their horrible Profanation of it. And at the laſt were forced to fly to the <hi>Secular Magiſtrate,</hi> from whom in times of Popery, when al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all Civil Magiſtrates were made their Slaves to execute their Luſts, they obtained ſeveral other things, which were civil Puniſhments of the Perſon that durſt adventure to ſtand their Sentence of Excommunication. He might not be either <hi>Judg or Witneſs in any Court.</hi> If he had occaſion to <hi>ſue any for his juſt Right in any Court, his Excommunication might be pleaded in bar to his Proceedings. If he ſtood excommunicated forty days,</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> might ſignify it to the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> and have from him a Writ to <hi>impriſon the Perſon</hi> to be kept <hi>without Bail or Mainprize,</hi> until he had given Satisfaction to the Church, and obtained its leave to come out. The Writ with us here in <hi>England</hi> made in Popiſh Times ran thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The King to the Sheriff of <hi>L.</hi> greeting; The Venerable Father <hi>H.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> hath ſignified to us by his Letters Patents, that <hi>B.</hi> a Member of his Dioceſe hath been Excommunicated, by his ordinary Authority, for his manifeſt Contumacy, and will not be reformed by the Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures; whereas the Royal Power ought not to be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98452:9"/>wanting to Holy Church in its Complaints, we command you to impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Body of the ſaid <hi>B.</hi> according to the Cuſtom of <hi>England,</hi> until he ſhall have ſatisfied Holy Church as well for his Contempt, as the Injury which he hath done unto it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>They not ſatisfied with this, obtained alſo another writ from the Civil Magiſtrate, commanding the <hi>burning</hi> of the Perſon whom they had once determined to be an <hi>Heretick;</hi> by virtue of which, many good Chriſtians were burned, as in former times, ſo in the time of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8th, and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> of which our <hi>Martyrology</hi> ſpeaks ſufficiently; but this is by a late Act deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>Being furniſhed with this Power, they were buſy enough in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it, and themſelves found Inconveniences ariſing from the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant uſe of it, ſo as even the <hi>Canon Law</hi> it ſelf regulated divers things. Among others it ordained a threefold <hi>Caution,</hi> for ſuch as were Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, upon the giving of any of which they were to be diſcharged, even by the <hi>Canon Law.</hi> A <hi>Caution by Pledg,</hi> a <hi>Caution by Sureties,</hi> and a <hi>Caution by Oath;</hi> that is, the Party was either to lay in ſome <hi>Cledg</hi> to the Biſhop, or enter into a <hi>Bond with Sureties,</hi> or take an <hi>Oath</hi> that he would afterwards <hi>be obedient to the Commands of the Church in form of Law,</hi> and upon this he was to be abſolved. The Caution by <hi>Oath,</hi> was only admitted, in caſe the Party was able to give no other, as appears from the Canon Law, <hi>Sexti decretat. l.</hi> 5. <hi>tit.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>But the Civil Power even in the times of Popery, quickly found the unreaſonable Inconveniences, accruing to the Nation, by this extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Power formerly either indulged to, or uſurped by <hi>Church-men,</hi> which it took care to reſtrain by ſeveral <hi>Statutes and Writs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this purpoſe was the <hi>Writ of Prohibition</hi> invented: I cannot tell the juſt Original of it, but it appears by the Statute of <hi>Circumſpecte aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> made 13 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. (that was 1285, that is now near 400 Years ſince) that it was before that time in uſe; for that Statute reſtraineth the iſſuing of it in Caſes of <hi>Fornication, and Adultery, leaving the Church-yard uncloſed, or the Church uncovered; in caſe of Oblations, and accuſtomed Tithes, and in caſe of Mortuaries and Penſions, Defamation and laying vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Hands on Clerks.</hi> By which it is plain, it was in uſe before that time, and that before that time <hi>Prohabitions</hi> were wont to iſſue, when any was queſtioned for theſe things in the <hi>Courts Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the Error of ſome, that Writs of <hi>Prohibition</hi> do not lye, where the matter is not cognoſcible in the <hi>Spiritual Court,</hi> but properly belongs to the Court Eccleſiaſtical. But Dr. <hi>Cozens</hi> in his <hi>Apology</hi> for Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Proceedings, <hi>pag.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17. gives us a much truer Notion of that Writ, telling us, <hi>The Prohibition is a Charge by the King's Writ, to forbear
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98452:10"/>to hold Plea either in ſome matter or manner, which it is ſuppoſed a Man dealeth in beyond his Juriſdiction, or otherwiſe than the Law will warrant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Writ of <hi>Prohibition</hi> commanding the Eccleſiaſtical Court to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no further, may be had not only where the thing doth properly belong to the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court;</hi> but alſo where they proceed in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner which the Laws of <hi>England</hi> do forbid. As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. If an Eccleſiaſtical Court will proceed, before they have given the Party accuſed a true Copy of Articles, a Prohibition lies upon the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute 2 <hi>Hen.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Alſo whether in caſe of a <hi>Proſecution by Informers,</hi> if the Court will proceed before the Informer, hath done what is required by the Statute 18 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 15. and other Statutes made to regulate Informers, a Prohibition will not lye in thoſe Caſes?</p>
               <p n="3">3. According to the Canon Law, alſo every Proſtor ought to have a Letter Procuratory, under the Hand and Seal of him who imployeth him: And an Act of Court ought to be made to admit him as a Proctor for ſuch Perſons; and if this be not, the Party proſecuted can recover no Charge, becauſe there is no Legal Adverſary to recover it from. By that Law alſo, voluntary Promoters (which may be Vagrants) ought firſt to give Security to pay Charges if over thrown. If the Eccleſiaſtical Judg refuſeth theſe things, Query, <hi>Whether a Prohibition will not lye?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. By the Canon Law alſo, <hi>Vox unius, eſt nox millius,</hi> No one Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs makes a Proof. If a Judg in thoſe Courts will give Sentence upon the Proof of a ſingle Witneſs, a Prohibition will lye.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If the Judg of an Eccleſiaſtical Court, will allow a Perſon to be charged <hi>generally, or incertainly,</hi> it is againſt the <hi>Common Law of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Judg in that caſe will prohibit the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So in many other Caſes, where the manner of the Proceedings in the Court Eccleſiaſtical, is either plainly againſt the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Canon Law Rules,</hi> or againſt the known Rules of Common Law; ſo that I conceive a <hi>Prohibition is, A Common law-writ forbidding the Eccleſiaſtical Judg to proceed, either in a Caſe which doth belong to his Juriſdiction, or in ſuch a manner, as is manifeſtly againſt the Rules of the Civil and Canon Law, according to which he ought to judg; or againſt the Common, or Statute Laws of this Realm, of which, and the true ſenſe of which his Majeſties Judges in the Courts at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>are the Judges, and the Benefit of which is the Liberty of every Subject of</hi> England.</p>
               <p>Theſe Prohibitions are ſometimes granted <hi>abſolutely</hi> in ſome Cauſes, with a <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> till the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judg</hi> amendeth his illegal Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; nor was this the only Writ in theſe Cauſes.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98452:10"/>
               <p> If Eccleſiaſtical Judges ſhould adventure to diſobey theſe Writs, the Law in that Caſe provided a <hi>Writ of Attachment:</hi> That in caſe the Eccleſiaſtical Judg would adventure to proceed, notwithſtanding ſuch a <hi>Writ of Prohibition,</hi> he might be forced to yield Obedience to it: Of this are many Inſtances in the Regiſter of Writs.</p>
               <p>And in regard the Eccleſiaſtical Judges might have ſo far proceeded, notwithſtanding ſuch <hi>Prohibition,</hi> as the Party might be laid up in Priſon upon the Writ <hi>de Excommanicato capiendo,</hi> the Law in that caſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Writ of <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> to deliver the Perſon out of Priſon, to follow his <hi>Attachment of the Judg, for his Contempt of the King's Writ of Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> There is a notable Precedent of this Writ in the Regiſtry of Writs, which, becauſe it is not known to all, I ſhall take the pains to tranſlate, for the benefit of ſuch Perſons, as may fall under theſe illegal extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Oppreſſions, and not know what to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The King to the Sheriff greeting, <hi>&amp;c. A. B.</hi> hath ſhewed us that whereas <hi>C. D.</hi> hath ſued him in the Court Chriſtian, before <hi>R.</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Debts and Chattels, which belong not to Teſtaments or Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, and altho the ſame <hi>A. B.</hi> hath delivered <hi>R.</hi> our Letter of Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, forbidding him to proceed in the Cauſe aforeſaid; yet the ſaid <hi>R.</hi> nevertheleſs, hath proceeded in the ſaid Court, contrary to our ſaid Prohibition; for which we have according to the Cuſtom, commanded <hi>R.</hi> to be attatched by our Letters directed to him to appear before our Juſtices, to ſhew cauſe why he proceeded in the Eccleſiaſtical Court contrary to our Prohibition; and for as much as the aforeſaid <hi>R.</hi> whiles the Plea of Attachment hath been depending before our ſaid Juſtices aforeſaid, as is afore ſaid, hath maliciouſly procured the ſaid <hi>A. B.</hi> to be taken, that ſo he might hinder him from proſecuting the ſaid Attachment before our Juſtices, according to the Laws and Cuſtoms of our Kingdom: We command you that if it be ſo, that you by no means execute our Writ for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of him, the ſaid <hi>A.</hi> upon the Occaſion aforeſaid, until the Plea of the ſaid Attachment be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in our Court, before our ſaid Juſtices, according to the Laws and Cuſtoms of our Kingdom; and if you have taken him upon the account aforeſaid, we command you to deliver him from the Priſon, in which upon that account he is detained in the mean time.</q> This Writ ſaith the Regiſter, iſſueth out of the Chancery, if the Party be taken, and impriſoned before the return of the <hi>Attachment,</hi> if it be in the time of the <hi>Vacation;</hi> otherwiſe it iſſueth out of the other Courts after the <hi>Attachment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like Writ iſſueth, if the Eccleſiaſtical Judg proceeded after an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, provided the <hi>Appeal</hi> be made appear to the Court by ſome publick
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98452:11"/>Inſtrument, and the Party obtaining it proveth by Witneſſes, or by Oath, that he is diligent in the Proſecution of his Appeal; and it muſt be within the compaſs of a Year after his Appeal.</p>
               <p>By which two Writs, appear the illegal and extravagant Proceedings in thoſe times by Judges in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, proceeding to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate Perſons,</hi> and then to certify againſt them and impriſon them, both contrary to the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> and in contempt of the King's Writs from thence, and alſo contrary to the Rules of their own Law, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which, after an Appeal, the inferiour Court ought to proceed no further, till the Cauſe was by the Judg <hi>ad quem,</hi> remitted to them.</p>
               <p>Nor was the <hi>Writ.</hi> of <hi>Prohibition,</hi> and the Writs of <hi>Attachment</hi> and <hi>Superſedcas</hi> relating to that Writ, the only Writs, that were invented in thoſe moſt corrupt and <hi>Popiſh Times,</hi> to relieve the Subjects oppreſſed in and by the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts;</hi> for there are many Cauſes in which <hi>Prohibitions</hi> will not lye, where thoſe Courts may proceed, and excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and after forty days ſignify, and have a Writ out againſt the Perſon to impriſon him; now that they might not at their Pleaſure keep Men in Priſon to their Ruine, the common Law hath provided of ancient Times a Writ <hi>de Cautione admittenda:</hi> Becauſe it is but little underſtood, I will give my <hi>Reader</hi> ſome account of it. The old <hi>Popiſh Canon Law</hi> had ordained, that if a Perſon were excommunicated right, or wrong, he ſhould not be abſolved, unleſs he gave a fitting Caution to obey the Commands of the Church in form of Law.</p>
               <p>This appeareth from that part of the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> which is called the <hi>ſixth</hi> of the <hi>Decretals.</hi> Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> in the Year 1294, ſet two Biſhops to gather up the <hi>Decretals</hi> of ſome former Popes, and to be added: to five of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, and to ſome of his own, and the Book to be called <hi>Sextus,</hi> upon which <hi>Johannes Andreas,</hi> a <hi>Bononian,</hi> gloſſed. Now in this part of the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> we read it again, and again enjoined, that Perſons excommunicated, ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be abſolved, unleſs they gave Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſee <hi>Sexti Decretal. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. <hi>de uſuris Sol.</hi> 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>Tit.</hi> 11. The <hi>Gloſſator</hi> upon that part of the <hi>Law</hi> every where expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that term of a <hi>fitting Caution:</hi> That a <hi>fitting Caution</hi> may be <hi>fide-juſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> or, <hi>Pignoratitia,</hi> or, <hi>Juratoria;</hi> that is, by <hi>Sureties,</hi> by <hi>Pledg,</hi> or by an <hi>Oath.</hi> He alſo determineth the <hi>Caution by Oath</hi> only to be taken, where the Party ſhould not be able to give Security, by Bond, and <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> nor by <hi>Pledg.</hi> The <hi>Caution</hi> by Sureties was looked upon as the greateſt Caution, and therefore in our Law, in a Writ to the <hi>Sheriff,</hi> commanding him to take <hi>Caution</hi> of a Party thus impriſoned (which we find in our <hi>Regiſt. Brevium</hi> p. 67.) commands him to take <hi>Cautionem
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98452:11"/>ſaltem Pignoratitiam,</hi> at leaſt a Caution by Pledge. But notwithſtanding this, that Men may ſee how natural a deſire it is in ſome kind of Men, to torment their Brethren, the Church here in <hi>England</hi> having got a Priviledge of a Writ to impriſon the Perſon, that had ſtood <hi>Forty days Excommanicated,</hi> they would keep Men in Priſon as long as they pleaſed, till they compelled them to do and pay what they liſted, tho they offered them <hi>Caution,</hi> according to the <hi>Canon Law.</hi> Let us hear what Doctor <hi>Cozens,</hi> in his Apology for certain proceedings in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. ſays of this Writ of <hi>Excommunicato capiendo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is (ſaith he) a Liberty peculiar to this Church of <hi>England,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the Realms in Chriſtendom, that I read of, that if a Man ſtand wilfully forty days together Excommunicated, and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly certified by the Biſhop into the Chancery, that then he is to be committed to Priſon, by Virtue of a Writ directed to the Sheriff; nothwithſtanding that in one Precedent (in the Regiſter) of this Writ, it is ſaid, <hi>Quod hujuſmodi Breve noſtrum ex gratiâ noſtrâ pracedat.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>By which it appears, that no Nation under Heaven gives Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſuch a Power; for the Perſon being impriſoned, is to lye there without <hi>Bail:</hi> No <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> no <hi>Action</hi> or <hi>Indictment upon Magna Charta,</hi> no Writ <hi>do Odio &amp; Atia,</hi> no Writ <hi>de homine plegiande,</hi> will help him; no nor any <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> unleſs the Impriſonment in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the King's Writ of <hi>Prohibition,</hi> or an <hi>Attachment,</hi> or <hi>Appeal</hi> Depending.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prelates,</hi> their <hi>Chancellours,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſaries,</hi> in times of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> never had any Inch of Power given into their hands, to torment Chriſtians, but they uſed it, and ſtretched it to an Ell; ſo many are the Inſtances of this, almoſt in every Leaf of the book of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> that he that reads it, will think all thoſe <hi>Officials</hi> were deſcended from <hi>Canibals,</hi> or thoſe the <hi>Roman Hiſtorian</hi> tells us, which he ſays, were <hi>Homines ad ſtragem Humans generis nati;</hi> Men born to the ruine of Mankind. This inforced our Forefathers here in <hi>England</hi> in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Popiſh Times,</hi> (having given the <hi>Prelates</hi> a Power to command them to execute their Paſſions, having Excommunicated Men right or wrong, to take out a Writ after forty Days, to Impriſon them without remedy, till they were ſatisfied) to deviſe another Writ to retrench a little their Power in this matter; This is called the Writ <hi>de Cautione admittenda.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98452:12"/>
               <p> I cannot find the <hi>Original</hi> of this Writ; it was certainly before any Statutes in our ordinary Statute Books; nor do I remember any notice they take of it: it is in one Regiſter of Writs, and it is mentioned by Dr. <hi>Cozens</hi> in his <hi>Apology</hi> for ſome <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Proceedings, <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. where he doth give a large and full account; and he who underſtands <hi>Latine,</hi> and will look into the <hi>Regiſter of Writs,</hi> will find it to be a true one, and may there read at large the form of the Writs; altho in thoſe times the whole Magiſtracy of the Nation were <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and ſo by their Principles more inſlav'd to thoſe they call the <hi>Church,</hi> then any <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> are; and yet it is very remarkable what care they took for the Liberty of the Subject in this one particular.</p>
               <p>In our <hi>Regiſter</hi> of <hi>Original Writs,</hi> Fol. 65. <hi>are the Writs for taking and impriſoning the Party Excommunicated,</hi> having ſtood ſo forty days. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately follow the King's Writs for his Delivery, upon his giving ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Caution.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Fol.</hi> 66. (ſaith the ſame Regiſter)</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If the Biſhop refuſeth to receive from ſuch an Excommunicated Perſon Impriſoned, a fitting Caution to obey the Commands of the Church in Form of Law, having a mind to oppreſs the Perſon Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, then he may ſend a Friend to the Court, and he ſhall have a Writ.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt to the Biſhop, (the Copy of which there follows) where the King tells him, He wonders at his refuſing the Caution offered; then commanding him to take it, and to deliver the Priſoner; then tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that in caſe he doth not do it, he himſelf will do what is his part to do.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the <hi>Biſhop</hi> doth not preſently deliver it, he ſhall have a ſecond Writ to the <hi>High Sheriff,</hi> commanding them to go to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and to require him to take the <hi>Caution,</hi> and to deliver the Priſoner; and alſo commanding him to do it himſelf, if the <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſhall refuſe to do it in his preſence.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He may have <hi>Atias's &amp; Pluries</hi> in both theſe Cauſes. But in caſe the Sheriff ſhall not obey, he ſhall have another Writ to the <hi>Coroner,</hi> commanding him <hi>to take Security of the Sheriff to appear ſuch a Day, in his Majeſties's Court, at</hi> Weſtminiſter, <hi>to ſhew reaſon why he contemneth the King's Writs; and alſo commanding the Coroeer himſelf to take the Caution, and to deliver the Priſoner.</hi> If the Biſhop indeed ſuſpects the Sheriff will deliver the Priſoner <hi>without Caution,</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> may have a Writ to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98452:12"/>
               <p> So careful were our Fore-fathers for the Liberty of the Subjects Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Dr. <hi>Cozens,</hi> a great <hi>Civilian,</hi> gives the <hi>Reader</hi> a full account of all this in his before mentioned <hi>Apology;</hi> and the learned <hi>Reader</hi> may him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf find all this in the Regiſter of <hi>Original Writs,</hi> 66, 67. from whence I infer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That by Law, the Common Law of <hi>England,</hi> and the Ancient <hi>Canon Law,</hi> every Biſhop is bound to take ſuch Caution, eſpecially <hi>fidejuſſory Caution,</hi> by <hi>Bond and Sureties,</hi> and to <hi>abſolve the Priſoner Excommunicated,</hi> tho he will not take an <hi>Oath</hi> to <hi>obey the Commands of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That if he will not do it till the Perſon be in Priſon, he hath no remedy; the Biſhop is a Tranſgreſſor of the Law, that is all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That if he be in Priſon, the Writ <hi>Originally</hi> was to be granted of Courſe, paying the <hi>ordinary Fees to the Curſitor.</hi> For the <hi>Rubrick</hi> doth not ſay, he ſhall move the <hi>Judges,</hi> or <hi>Petition</hi> any; but <hi>he may ſend a Friend to the Court,</hi> and have the Writ.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That if the Biſhop will not obey, he ſhall have no <hi>Attachment</hi> againſt the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> (in Popiſh times Biſhops Perſons were too facred for ſuch things) but he nay if he will, have a ſecond and third Writ to the Biſhop.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If he chuſeth it rather, he ought to have the ſecond Writ to the <hi>High Sheriff,</hi> and that in Courſe too, according to the Regiſter.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If the <hi>Sheriff</hi> will not obey it, he may (if he will) take out a ſecond and a third, or more Writs to the <hi>Sheriff;</hi> but if he will not, he may have an <hi>Attachment</hi> againſt the <hi>Sheriff</hi> ſent to the <hi>Coroners,</hi> with a Writ commanding them to take the <hi>Caution,</hi> and to deliver the <hi>Priſoner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. That all this is but the old <hi>Common Law</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and a juſt Enforcement of the Biſhop to do what he ought to have done, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any of this in Obedience to the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> which the <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Men</hi> pretend to be their Rule; and this is but an Enforcement of them to keep to their own Rules, and therefore the moſt juſt thing imaginable.</p>
               <p>Here a Queſtion may be ſtarted, What ſuch a Perſon that is Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated and Impriſoned muſt do, over and above giving a <hi>cantionary Bond</hi> to be diſcharged?</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether he is by the Law obliged to deſire Abſolution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether he be bound to pay the Charges of the Proſecutor?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt Caſe, we muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt the Caſe of one that is <hi>Legally Excommunicated,</hi> and one that is <hi>Excommisnicated Illegally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Perſon be Illegally Excommunicated, I cannot ſee how he can
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98452:13"/>avoid the deſire of and obtaining Abſolution, becauſe this is the Courſe of the <hi>Canon Law.</hi> If he be <hi>Illegally Excommunicated,</hi> and the King's Courts have ſo determined it, and by their <hi>Writ</hi> of <hi>Prohibition,</hi> have commanded the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts</hi> to proceed no further; and if they have Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him, to <hi>abſolve him;</hi> He is not in this Caſe bound to beg it of them; he hath begged the hearing of his Cauſe by the <hi>King's Courts of Juſtice;</hi> they have determined him no Tranſgreſſor; what hath he to ask them Pardon, or Abſolution for? There is more reaſon for his abſolving them, for they are thoſe who have done the wrong: Nor is it uſual, when an Appeal is againſt an unjuſt Excommunication by an Inferiour <hi>Officials</hi> Court, for the Party appealing to beg <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> of the Court, that is preſumed to have wronged him; he is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved of Courſe from the <hi>Superiour Court.</hi> It is true, The Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> do not <hi>abſolve Perſons,</hi> but they command them to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; nor is the Party further bound to beg it; they are to yield Obedience to the <hi>King's Writ,</hi> and to do it.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond thing, it is the moſt unreaſonable thing that can be imagined; and thoſe who inſiſt upon it muſt <hi>aliquid monſtri alere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſame Judge Eccleſiaſtical that decrees Excommunication in any Caſe of Contumacy, hath alſo a Power <hi>to condemn the Party ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in Coſts of Suit;</hi> which being done, if the Coſts taxed be legal, he to whom they are decreed, hath a legal way to recover them, and no Biſhop can juſtify an inſiſting upon the Payment of them before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Priſoner. Admit that at the Suit of any Perſon, one be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, the perſon judging himſelf falſly Impriſoned, brings his Writ of <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> or his Writ <hi>de Odio &amp; Atia,</hi> or <hi>de Homine replegiando,</hi> or any other Writ, and ſo brings himſelf before a Superiour Judge; he upon the hearing the Cauſe, judgeth the Plaintiff wrong'd, and diſchargeth him from his Impriſonment. Was it ever heard of, or can any ſuch a thing be imagined, in a Court of Juſtice, that the Judge ſhould refuſe to deliver the Priſoner, till he hath agreed to pay the Charges his Adverſary hath been at, in doing him that Wrong?</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Duty of the Judge Eccleſiaſtical in this Caſe, is to be learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Writ, which commandeth him no more than <hi>to take the Caution, and deliver the Priſoner;</hi> if indeed the Writ ſaid, <hi>firſt paying the Charges of the Suit,</hi> it were another Caſe; but it ſaith no ſuch thing, nor is there any reaſon it ſhould; for poſſibly the Proſecution hath been wholly Illegal, Injurious, and Malicious; and it is too much to pay a Perſon for playing the Knave. But it may be juſtly admired, why, when theſe Proſecutors having overthrown their Adverſaries, and ſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98452:13"/>are in a Capacity to have Coſts of Suit taxed by the Judge: They are yet ſo cautious as to ſollicit <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judges,</hi> not to diſcharge ſuch Priſoners in Obedience to the King's Writ, till they have paid the Charges, or ingaged to pay them. May it not be preſumed, that the Charges they would have thus ſecured, are illegal Extortions, which they would have confirmed, and come into by the Authority of the <hi>Judge Eccleſiaſtical?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. I would gladly ſee it tried, Whether if the Eccleſiaſtical Judge ſhould make a return upon the Writ <hi>de Cautione admittenda,</hi> that he could not diſcharge the Perſon becauſe he refuſed to pay the Proſecutor's Charges, whether that would by the Lord Chancellor be judged a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and Juſtifiable return to a Writ, which requireth no ſuch thing? I do humbly conceive, that all the Legal Returns that can be made to ſuch a Writ are, either,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>There is no ſuch Perſon in Priſon upon my Denunciation:</hi> Or,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>He refuſeth to give me fitting Caution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What may be reckoned a fitting and ſufficient Caution</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Cozens,</hi> in his before mentioned <hi>Apology, p.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2.) <hi>I find not determined or colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible out of the Books of Common Law.</hi> But I am ſure the Doctor was not ſuch a Stranger to the <hi>Sexti Decretalia,</hi> as not to know it is expreſſed there three or four times over; either <hi>Fidejuſſoria</hi> by Sureties, or <hi>Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noratitia</hi> by Pawn or Pledg, or <hi>Juratoria</hi> by Oath. And indeed the Doctor tells us of all theſe in the <hi>Civil Law.</hi> If the Doctor means that the <hi>Common Law</hi> hath not determined the <hi>Quantum</hi> of the <hi>Bond,</hi> or Pledge, I am apt to believe it will be judged otherways, <hi>viz.</hi> That no greater <hi>Quantum</hi> ſhall be inſiſted upon, than hath before been uſually given in the Caſe, which I have not heard to have exceeded 10, or at moſt 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> Nor indeed is there any reaſon any great Sum ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on: For if the contempt be for not appearing at Court, ſurely that is enough to ſecure that. If it be not obeying <hi>an Order or Decree,</hi> if the Decree be a juſt Decree, for making ſome Satisfaction in caſe of Wrong, the Canon Law allowes no <hi>Caution</hi> till that be done, neither I believe will the Common Law; for the Common Law in this Caſe is plainly in Affirmance of the Canon Law, which in former times was the Law <hi>Paramount,</hi> and is ſo ſtill in <hi>Popiſh Countries.</hi> Now the <hi>Canon Law allowing Caution,</hi> the cuſtom of the Nation which is the <hi>Common Law,</hi> came in to inforce <hi>Ecceſiaſtical Judges,</hi> to keep to the Rule of their own Law, and innovate nothing to the Prejudice of the Subjects <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Perſon.</hi> Thus far I have ſhewed what remedy the Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath provided for the Oppreſſions of the Subjects in the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Courts, either by way of <hi>Prohibition,</hi> Writs of <hi>Attachment</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98452:14"/>
                  <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> or the Writ <hi>de Cautions admittenda.</hi> Several Statutes have alſo provided againſt the Extravagancies of their Power in other things. The <hi>Stat.</hi> 25. <hi>Henry</hi> 8.19. provides againſt the <hi>Church-men's making or putting in Practice any Canons, which have not firſt had the King's aſſent,</hi> or any <hi>Canons contrariant or repugnant to the Laws and Statutes of the Land.</hi> The <hi>Scari.</hi> 5. <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. provides againſt their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, refuſing to give a true Copy of the Libel. The <hi>Stat.</hi> 23. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.9. provides againſt Citation of Perſons out of the Dioceſs; and taking above a 3d. for a Citation. 21 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.5. provides againſt Extortion by them, in the <hi>Probates of Wills.</hi> So in many other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; but I ſhall keep to my Theme, to declare what I have found in the Law of <hi>England,</hi> with Reference to <hi>Excommunications.</hi> There is one Statute more, which relates to the Writ <hi>de Excommunicato ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendo:</hi> It is that, 5. <hi>Elizab.</hi> 23. which commands, that thoſe Writs ſhall not be iſſued but in <hi>Term time; That they ſhall have at leaſt twenty days betwixt the Teſt and the Return;</hi> that they ſhall be entered upon <hi>Record</hi> in the <hi>King's Bench,</hi> &amp;c. And that no <hi>Capias</hi> ſhall further iſſue out but in <hi>ten Caſes</hi> there expreſſed; with many other things. When it will pleaſe our Parliament to conſider, whether the Writ <hi>de Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> ſhould be continued, or run the ſame fate with that Couſin to it, <hi>de Hereticis comburendis,</hi> I cannot tell; but certainly it is very unreaſonable, that the Civil Magiſtrate ſhould be by it haled in, to ruine Perſons and Families, whoſe Guilt was never proved before him, and be but Servants to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judges,</hi> to confirm, their it may be, paſſionate, as well as unjuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Decrees. Perſons that are imployed to take away the Lives, Liberties or Goods of any Perſons, had certainly need to be firſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that they have done ſomething worthy of Death or Bonds, or ſuch Degrees of Puniſhment; and not think it enough that a Judge of any Eccleſiaſtical Court tells them ſo; let them take them and judge them according to their Law (as <hi>Pilate</hi> told the <hi>Jews.</hi>) Doth the excellent Law of <hi>England</hi> (unleſs that Part of it, which roſe up, or was made not only in <hi>Popiſh times,</hi> but from <hi>Popiſh Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> only relating to the Church) condemn any to the loſs of <hi>Life, Limb, Liberty,</hi> or <hi>Eſtate,</hi> before thoſe who are to execute that Part of it, have had the leaſt Liberty to hear the Subject ſpeak for himſelf? Are Proteſtant <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> to believe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Officers</hi> (now by a ſtrange <hi>Catachreſis</hi> called the Church) in high Acts of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98452:14"/>
               <p> Will any ſay, that <hi>their Law gives them no Power to impriſon</hi> any? (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>perhaps Clergy-men, for Adultery or Fornication.</hi>) I remember the <hi>Jews</hi> told <hi>Pilate</hi> much the ſame thing, concerning Chriſt; but how eaſy is the Anſwer, that neither doth the Law of God, from whence they pretend to derive <hi>Excommunication,</hi> appoint any ſuch Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> to the ruine of Families, upon Perſons <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated?</hi> But be this as it will, the Law of <hi>England</hi> at preſent is ſo, and muſt be, tho not approved, yet ſubmitted to, until it pleaſeth God to give our <hi>Parliaments</hi> Hearts and Leiſure to enquire into the Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, and Righteouſneſs of it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:98452:15"/>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98452:15"/>
            <head>PART II. THE CASE and CURE; OR The miſchievous Conſequents of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>EXcommunications</hi> being ſo commonly <hi>thundered</hi> out (to uſe the Law-Term for them) by <hi>Perſons</hi> who have no <hi>immediate Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from Chriſt</hi> to trade in them, and for ſuch <hi>crivial Crimes,</hi> as no <hi>Law of God</hi> hath ordered them againſt, and in ſuch a <hi>light, and precipitant manner,</hi> as no part of God's Word warranteths; The wiſer ſort of Men, look upon them rather as <hi>Excomonings</hi> (much a kin to the <hi>Romanis, Interdico tibi aquâ &amp; igni,</hi> Civil Puniſhments) than the <hi>Solemn Inſtitutions of God,</hi> and thereupon have no dread of any <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Influence,</hi> or <hi>Effect</hi> of them; and therefore overmuch ſlight them, not being well aware, that as they are a piece of our <hi>Common Law,</hi> ſo they have <hi>Legal Puniſhments</hi> (heavy enough) annexed to them, which if duly conſidered, were enough to make Men more wary how they incur them, if they can by any means avoid them. Nor if they be once catch'd in this Knot (<hi>Innodati</hi> ſaith the <hi>Common Law</hi> Writ) doth every one well underſtand how to ſlip, or unty it. That therefore every one may pay that <hi>juſt reſpect</hi> which he oweth unto the <hi>Law</hi> in this caſe; or at leaſt take heed to himſelf, and avoid his own Danger; I ſhall briefly ſhew the danger that Man <hi>runs,</hi> who ſuffers himſelf to be <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and the <hi>proper way</hi> which the Law hath provided, to <hi>avoid it;</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Remedy which the Law hath provided for them who are fallen under the <hi>misfortune</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt place; He that is <hi>Excommunicated, is forthwith diſabled to ſue in his Majeſties Civil Courts.</hi> Not that the <hi>Excommunication</hi> takes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98452:16"/>away his Right to <hi>ſue</hi> for his <hi>juſt Rights,</hi> but that it may <hi>in time</hi> be pleaded in <hi>Abatement of his Action.</hi> But concerning this, note whoſoever is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental, in <hi>procuring, ſolliciting, decreeing,</hi> or <hi>pronouncing</hi> the <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> ſhall never plead it; nor ſhall it be pleaded unleſs the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication</hi> be <hi>ſignified</hi> by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> himſelf; for the <hi>Court</hi> will receive no <hi>Certificate</hi> from any Perſon in this Caſe, to whom (if they ſee cauſe) they cannot <hi>write</hi> to abſolve the Perſon. Nor ſhall it be pleaded after that <hi>Iſſue is joined;</hi> and <hi>query,</hi> whether it ſhall be pleaded, unleſs <hi>the Cauſe</hi> be expreſly mentioned in the <hi>Significavit? for which,</hi> and the <hi>time</hi> when the Perſon was <hi>Excommunicated;</hi> nor if it be at length admitted by the <hi>Court,</hi> ſhall it <hi>deſtroy the Action;</hi> it ſhall only <hi>abate</hi> it until the <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> be taken off.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Albeit an <hi>excommunicate Perſon</hi> may be appointed an <hi>Executor,</hi> and is <hi>capable</hi> of a <hi>Legacy;</hi> yet ſo long as he ſtandeth <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> he is not to be admitted by the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> nor can <hi>commence any Suit</hi> for his <hi>Legacy</hi> in the <hi>Court Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> See <hi>Swinborn of Wills</hi> p. 5. §. 6. p. 228.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If a Perſon be <hi>excommunicated</hi> for <hi>Hereſy,</hi> or <hi>manifeſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> or with an <hi>Anathema,</hi> he <hi>cannot make a Will,</hi> but in other caſes he may, ſaith the ſame Author, <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>§.</hi> 22. p. 62.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Perſon <hi>Excommunicated</hi> cannot (ſay ſome) give his <hi>Suffrage in any Elections,</hi> no not of <hi>Parliament-Men;</hi> but this is an idle Dream, ſo long as he hath a <hi>Freehold of</hi> 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> a Year. Some will have it too, that he cannot <hi>marry;</hi> but Marriage being <hi>de Jure Naturali,</hi> no learned <hi>Canoniſt</hi> would ever affirm it. But I have known a <hi>Miniſter</hi> queſtioned in our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> and (if not <hi>ſuſpended)</hi> yet ſmartly threatned with <hi>Suſpenſion,</hi> for <hi>marrying a Perſon</hi> that was <hi>Excommunicated;</hi> but this is but the <hi>Extravagancy</hi> of that Court's Proceedings.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The great danger of all is, <hi>If a Perſon be excommunicated</hi> (whether it be <hi>legally</hi> or <hi>injuriouſly)</hi> and ſtand ſo forty days; upon the <hi>Certificate of it</hi> into the <hi>High Court of Chancery,</hi> a Writ is to iſſue out of the <hi>High Court of Chancery</hi> to the <hi>Sheriff</hi> of the <hi>County</hi> in which the Perſon lives, to <hi>impriſon</hi> him till he hath given <hi>Satisfaction to the Biſhop.</hi> Being thus <hi>impriſoned,</hi> he is not to be delivered by any of the <hi>ordinary Writs</hi> for the <hi>Liberty of the Subject's Perſon,</hi> nor unleſs he ſubmits to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and offers Caution for the time to come, to <hi>ſtand</hi> to, and <hi>obey the Commands of the Church, in form of Law;</hi> this <hi>Caution</hi> may be by a Bond of 10 or 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or by a <hi>Pledg,</hi> or if the Party can do none of theſe, by his <hi>Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Writ to impriſon the <hi>Perſon excommunicated,</hi> is in no Nation of the World but only in this: But here it is <hi>Common-Law</hi> (while it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our Parliament by a <hi>Statute</hi> to amend the <hi>Common Law</hi> in that point)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98452:16"/>the Subject therefore had need underſtand both. 1. <hi>How by Law, to avoid Excommunication.</hi> 2. <hi>How to get himſelf out of Priſon, in caſe he be impriſoned upon this Writ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, He muſt know that no Perſon can be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, but upon <hi>Contempt</hi> or <hi>Contumacy,</hi> which may be;</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If the Perſon being duly cited, demeth, or omitteth to appear.</hi> If he be not perſonally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>oned, he needs not appear the firſt time; but then their way is to cite him by a Writ called <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; Mods,</hi> ſet up at the <hi>Door's of his Houſe,</hi> or at the <hi>Church-doors,</hi> citing him at a certain day to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to anſwer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If (being perſonally cited) he doth not appear the firſt time, or whether he be or no, if he doth not appear the ſecond time, he is excommunicated for Contempt. If he be cited perſonally, the Law is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clerk Praxis Cur. Eccleſ. Tis.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp; Tit.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>That he ſhall appear the third day after the ſervice of the Citation.</hi> The Law alſo is that, <hi>If he will give the Apparitor</hi> 6 d. <hi>he muſt bring him the full and true Copy of the Citation.</hi> If the day of Appearance, be not at leaſt the third day from the Citation, or if he hath before Witneſs given the <hi>Apparitor</hi> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> to bring him a full and true Copy of the Citation, I conceive he needs not appear, but liſten what they do; and if they decree him <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> he may appeal within fifteen days, and bring from the <hi>Superiour Court,</hi> an <hi>Inhibition</hi> to ſtop their Proceedings againſt him. And further, the Rule in that Law is, <hi>Totus dies debetur delinquenti:</hi> It is enough for a Perſon to appear any hour of the day (provided it be a <hi>Court-hour)</hi> wherein he is cited to appear; ſo as tho he be called before he comes, yet if he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that day, he ſhall be diſcharged; or he may <hi>appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When he appeareth, he ſhall demand his <hi>Charge,</hi> which is either by a <hi>Preſentment</hi> from <hi>Churchwardens;</hi> or by a <hi>Libel</hi> or <hi>Articles</hi> which are exhibited by a <hi>Promoter.</hi> Be it which it will, he ſhall demand a Copy; if it be <hi>denied</hi> or <hi>delaied,</hi> he ſhall bring (if he will) a <hi>Prohibition</hi> from the <hi>King's Court</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> forbidding them to proceed in that Cauſe, till they have given him a full and true Copy of his Charge, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Statute 5 <hi>Hen.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If he <hi>appeareth in Perſon, he ought to have his Charge the firſt Court-day:</hi> If he appeareth by a <hi>Proctor,</hi> they will uſually (to get the Proctors more Fees) give to the ſecond Court-day to bring in the <hi>Libel</hi> or <hi>Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. If they deliver him not his Charge the ſecond Court-day, he may <hi>appeal,</hi> if upon his Demand the Judg will not diſmiſs him; or he may, if he will, bring his <hi>Prohibition</hi> for want of <hi>Articles,</hi> and ſtop their further Proceedings.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98452:17"/> 5. If the Proceedings be upon a <hi>Promotion,</hi> and the <hi>Promoter</hi> hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed a <hi>Proctor</hi> in the Caſe, the Party accuſed muſt know, that no <hi>Proctor</hi> can be admitted without a <hi>Proxy,</hi> that is, Letters <hi>Procuratory</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Promoter's Hand and Seal,</hi> authoriſing him to act for him in the Caſe; and when he hath that, there muſt be an <hi>Act</hi> entred in <hi>Court,</hi> to admit ſuch a Perſon <hi>Proctor</hi> in the Caſe. The Party charged may go or ſend to the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> and demand a <hi>ſight of both thoſe.</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Law is this, Becauſe any <hi>Proctor</hi> is liable to the Party's <hi>Action,</hi> if he moleſteth any Perſon in the name of another, without <hi>Authority</hi> from him: And ſecondly, <hi>If there be no Act of Court</hi> admitting him as a <hi>Proctor,</hi> tho the Party accuſed be Conquerer in the Caſe; yet <hi>he cannot recover Coſts,</hi> becauſe there is no <hi>legal Adverſary</hi> againſt whom they can be recovered.</p>
            <p n="6">6. According to the <hi>Statute-Law, every Informer,</hi> if overthrown, ſhall pay <hi>Charges.</hi> According to the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Canon Law,</hi> none ought to be admitted as a <hi>Voluntary Promoter,</hi> till he hath given Security to pay the Charges if he be overthrown. The Party accuſed therefore ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he anſwereth the <hi>Articles,</hi> demand this; if it be denied by the Judg, he may <hi>appeal</hi> to the ſuperiour Court.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is alſo worth the Perſons inquiry who is accuſed, to be well adviſed by Lawyers, whether the <hi>Promoter</hi> in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> be not obliged to all thoſe things, that an <hi>Informer</hi> in the Secular Courts is tied to, by the Statutes 31 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 5.18 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Jac.</hi> 4. The Reaſon is, becauſe thoſe Statutes ſay, — <hi>Informers upon any Penal Statutes,</hi> and commonly <hi>Promoters</hi> in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> ſay ſuch and ſuch things are done contrary to the <hi>Statutes of this Realm, as well as contrary</hi> to the <hi>Canons:</hi> Now what things the <hi>Statutes,</hi> which alſo name <hi>Promoters,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of ſuch <hi>Informers</hi> and <hi>Promoters,</hi> the Statutes do declare.</p>
            <p n="8">8. When the Party accuſed hath a <hi>Copy</hi> of his <hi>Libel,</hi> let him demand time to anſwer; if the <hi>Judg</hi> denies him time (at leaſt till the next Court-day) let him <hi>appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Having due time granted, in the mean time let him duly conſider the <hi>matter and form of his Libel.</hi> As to which let him amongſt other things, obſerve theſe that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Whether the Matters he be charged with, belong to the Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court?</hi> If Lawyers tell him no, let that be his Anſwer, and let him haſten to bring his <hi>Prohibition,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es in all ſuch Cauſes.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Whether they have put into the <hi>Libel</hi> the <hi>Promoters Petition for Right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to be done him? I have ſeen it ſeveral times left out. It is a Rule in their Law, <hi>Libellus eſt ipſo jure nullus, ubi nihil petitur.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98452:17"/>If he finds that this is wanting, Let his Anſwer only be, <hi>That the Libel is in Law utterly void, and inſufficient, and deſire to be diſmiſſed:</hi> If the Judg refuſeth to <hi>diſmiſs him,</hi> let him <hi>appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Let him alſo obſerve, Whether he be in the Articles laid to be <hi>one of the Dioceſe, or a Pariſhioner of ſuch a Pariſh;</hi> for if it be not laid, it can never be <hi>proved,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Promoter</hi> muſt fail in his <hi>Sait;</hi> for what is not laid, cannot be proved: <hi>Quicquid deponitur extra Articulum, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponitur extra Legem,</hi> is a Rule in their Law. If he be laid to be a <hi>Pariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioner</hi> of ſuch a place, within ſuch a <hi>Dioceſe;</hi> let him not in his Anſwer confeſs it, but ſay, — <hi>He cannot determine the Bounds of Dioceſes and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, but for that he referreth himſelf to the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Let him alſo obſerve, If the things he be charged to have done, or omitted, be within the compaſs of a Year, and whether there hath ſince been no <hi>Act of Grace,</hi> or <hi>Oblivion, which hath pardoned them, and whether they be not ſuch things as he hath been puniſhed for,</hi> or <hi>ſuch things as the Statute Law hath limited the Proſecution of to a leſs time than a Year:</hi> For if any of theſe things be, they may be given in anſwer to avoid either the whole, or any part of the Charge. If the Judg will not accept the <hi>Anſwer,</hi> the Party may ſue out a <hi>Prohibition</hi> and ſtop them.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Let him alſo obſerve, <hi>Whether he be charged certainly, or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly,</hi> as to <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> or only <hi>generally and incertainly;</hi> if he be charged only generally, as for the moſt part he is, in Church-wardens <hi>Preſentments,</hi> not mentioning <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Place;</hi> or incertainly with <hi>or's,</hi> that he did not come to his Pariſh Church, ſuch and ſuch Months and Days, or was abſent in ſome one, or more, or moſt of them: Let his Anſwer be, that this Charge is <hi>void in Law,</hi> for the <hi>generality or incertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it.</hi> If the Judg will not receive his Anſwer, let him <hi>appeal;</hi> for the Law of <hi>England</hi> alloweth no ſuch Charges, <hi>from which can be no diſcharge;</hi> or where the Crime is not fixed to a certain time. But it may be, in this Caſe, a <hi>Prohibition</hi> will be his beſt remedy.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Let him obſerve, Whether he be charged only upon <hi>Statute Law,</hi> or upon <hi>Canons;</hi> if upon <hi>Canons,</hi> let him in his Anſwer modeſtly refer himſelf to <hi>Perſons learned in the Statute Laws,</hi> Whether any ſuch <hi>Canons</hi> were ever <hi>enacted, ratified, allowed, or confirmed by Parliament, or by the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Laws of the Land,</hi> as they ſtood in the Year 1639; and if not Whether they be not made void by the Statute 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="10">10. When he hath given his Anſwer, which muſt be ſubſcribed by his own hand, it is uſual for the <hi>Adverſe Proctor</hi> to demand a time to prove
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98452:18"/>his <hi>Articles,</hi> for which the <hi>Judg</hi> at his pleaſure granteth 2, 3, 4, or 6 <hi>Court</hi>-days (uſually but two) Let him alſo at the ſame time move, that he may have Liberty within that time alſo, to produce any <hi>Witneſſes</hi> for his Defence; if it be denied, let him <hi>appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. Let him obſerve, what time the Judge ſetteth his Adverſary to produce his Witneſſes in Court, and whom he names for Witneſſes for him. Let him alſo deſire a time to be ſet in Court for him to produce his <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and be careful to bring them at the time, for they muſt all be ſworn in the Court, then examined privately by the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Unleſs the Adverſary deſireth a <hi>Commiſſion to examine</hi> Witneſſes, (which is not often done, becauſe it is much more chargeable) in that Caſe, there are no Witneſſes in the Court produced and ſworn, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p n="12">12. If the <hi>Party Defendant</hi> will, he may deliver in to the Regiſter <hi>Interrogatories,</hi> upon which the <hi>Regiſter</hi> ſhall croſs-examine his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary's Witneſſes. But he muſt be very wary as to this, for he ſhall not afterward <hi>except</hi> againſt any of his <hi>Adverſary's Witneſſes,</hi> whom he hath croſs-examined, and made Witneſſes for himſelf.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Let him <hi>adviſe his own Witneſſes to be very careful, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter ſetteth down what they ſay, in their own Words, that under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> of putting them into a decent Phraſe, their whole ſenſe be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</p>
            <p n="14">14. When the <hi>time Probatory,</hi> ſet at firſt by the Judge, is expired, let him deſire of the Judge, <hi>Publication.</hi> If the <hi>Judge</hi> will grant longer time to prove, let him deſire the Advantage of the ſame time alſo, to bring more Witneſſes for himſelf, which he may, or may not, make uſe of as he pleaſes.</p>
            <p n="15">15. If once the Term given for Proof be expired, let him deſire <hi>Publication,</hi> and Liberty to take out a <hi>Copy of the Depoſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. When he hath got a <hi>Copy,</hi> let him diligently obſerve, if he can prove any thing contrary to what the Witneſſes, or any of them have ſworn, if he can, let him at the next <hi>Court-day,</hi> offer a Paper of <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Particular Exceptions,</hi> ſhewing the <hi>Particulars</hi> which he exepteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt in their <hi>Depoſitions</hi> ſeverally, as well as his <hi>General Exceptions</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them all. Let him deſire a time to bring in Witneſſes to prove his <hi>Exceptions.</hi> If the Judge refuſeth to admit his <hi>Exceptions,</hi> or to give him due time to prove them, he may again <hi>appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. When once the <hi>Promoter</hi> hath allowed to have <hi>Publication,</hi> he may again move for time, to invalidate the Proof of the <hi>Exceptions,</hi> but not to fortify his firſt Proof. If any Liberty of that nature be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98452:18"/>the <hi>Defendant</hi> may <hi>appeal;</hi> for unleſs in a Caſe for the <hi>King</hi> after Publication, no new Witneſſes can be produced.</p>
            <p n="18">18. When the Party againſt whom the <hi>Promotion</hi> is, peruſeth the <hi>Depoſitions,</hi> let him ſtrictly obſerve, whether the Particulars he is charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with be proved by <hi>two Witneſſes;</hi> for it is a Rule in their Law, <hi>Vox unius eſt vox nullius;</hi> and if the Judge will admit the thing proved by <hi>one Witneſs,</hi> a <hi>Prohibition</hi> lyes: For the <hi>King's Judges,</hi> will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee that thoſe Courts ſhall keep to matters truly belonging to their <hi>Juriſdiction;</hi> but alſo that in the Proſecution of them, they ſhall keep to the <hi>received Rules</hi> of their own Law, in thoſe main Points of Proof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. It is an uſual thing upon Preſentments by Church-wardens, when the Party preſented calls for Proof of the Preſentment, to tell him, That the <hi>Church-wardens Preſentment</hi> is a <hi>Conviction,</hi> they being <hi>ſworn Officers.</hi> But this is contrary to the <hi>Law of England,</hi> which alloweth no <hi>Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Officers ex Officio</hi> to be a <hi>Conviction.</hi> If <hi>Grand-Juries</hi> at <hi>Aſſizes</hi> and <hi>Seſſions</hi> do preſent, this is no <hi>Conviction,</hi> but the Perſon muſt after this be <hi>indicted,</hi> and <hi>Proof</hi> made by Witneſſes. If therefore the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court</hi> inſiſts on this, the Perſon may appeal; or (which it may be is better) he may have a <hi>Prohibition</hi> from the <hi>King's Court at Weſtminſter,</hi> as ſome Great Lawyers think.</p>
            <p n="20">20. When the <hi>time for Proof</hi> is expired, and <hi>Publication made,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions</hi> given in, and <hi>proved,</hi> and <hi>Publication of thoſe</hi> Proofs alſo made; Either Party may move for a time to be ſet to conclude, and to give the Judge <hi>Informations</hi> of the whole State, and Merit of the Caſe; and alſo to give ſentence in it.</p>
            <p n="21">21. At the Day ſet, the Party accuſed, or promoted againſt, may appear, and ſhow to the Judge the whole State of the Caſe, and plead it himſelf; or, if he will, by an <hi>Advocate,</hi> if any be at hand; or for ought I know, if there be none by, an <hi>Attorney,</hi> or <hi>Counſellour</hi> at <hi>Common Law;</hi> after which the Judge will appoint (upon deſire) a day to give Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p n="22">22. At that day the Party muſt have a Form of an <hi>Abſolutory Sentence,</hi> ready to tender to the Judge.</p>
            <p n="23">23. If the Judge gives Sentence againſt him, he may <hi>appeal</hi> within 15 days, by virtue of the Statute, 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.12.</p>
            <p n="24">24. All along the <hi>Proſecution,</hi> the Perſon againſt whom the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion is,</hi> ſhall do well after every Court, to get the <hi>Acts of the Count in his Caſe, under the Regiſter's Hand,</hi> and to keep them by him care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p n="25">25. This laſt <hi>Appeal</hi> is called, Appealing a <hi>Sentence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> definitive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98452:19"/>the definitive Sentence. All appealing before this, is but <hi>a Gravamine,</hi> from a Grievance, or an <hi>Interlocutory Decree</hi> inferring a Grievance.</p>
            <p>Becauſe there have been ſo frequent mentions in this Diſcourſe of Writs of <hi>Prohibition,</hi> and of <hi>Appeals,</hi> it may not be amiſs further to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the <hi>Reader</hi> of both theſe.</p>
            <p>And firſt, concerning <hi>Prohibitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Judges</hi> of the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Courts</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> are undoubtedly, under the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Keepers of the Liberties of England;</hi> and by their <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Oath,</hi> are to preſerve unto the Subjects, their <hi>Rights,</hi> and <hi>Liberties.</hi> Two things are the Rights of Subjects;</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be <hi>Impleaded</hi> for any ſuppoſed Offences, in <hi>Proper Courts,</hi> that is, ſuch as according to the Law of <hi>England,</hi> have a Cognizance of the ſuppoſed Offences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To be <hi>proſecuted</hi> in a juſt and reaſonable manner, according to the Rules of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Judges of his Majeſty's Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> are doubtleſs <hi>Judges,</hi> paramount to whoſe <hi>Judgments,</hi> all the Judgments given in other Courts, ſhall be ſubjected ſo far, as they ſhall determine (upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to them) <hi>Whether they have proceeded upon Matters, (within their Juriſdiction?) and Secondly, Whether they have proceeded according to the Rules of that Law, the Executors of which they are?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence if the Subject think himſelf grieved by the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> either becauſe he is there called in queſtion for Matters, which they have no <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> in; or becauſe <hi>he is not proſecuted according to Rutes of the Common Law of England,</hi> in all Cauſes; or the particular Rules of that Law which belongeth to ſuch Courts upon the Subjects Motion and <hi>Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion</hi> to that purpoſe: <hi>The Courts of the King's-Bench, Common Pleas,</hi> or <hi>Exchequer,</hi> grant a Writ of <hi>Prohibition,</hi> according to the Nature of the Complaint, either abſolutely forbidding them to proceed in ſuch a Caſe, or <hi>limitedly,</hi> until they have amended ſuch or ſuch an Error in their Proceedings.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judge</hi> thinks himſelf injured, he may have an hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and argue the Caſe: If the <hi>Secular Judges</hi> be convinced of any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, they will grant them a Writ of <hi>Conſultation,</hi> after the Receipt of which, they may proceed, notwithſtanding any former <hi>Prohibition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Appeals,</hi> the <hi>Reader</hi> muſt know that even in the vileſt and moſt <hi>Popiſh</hi> times, the Law of <hi>England</hi> never left the Subject to the Mercy of an <hi>Inferiour Arbitrary Judge,</hi> in a <hi>Court Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> but gave him a Liberty to <hi>appeal</hi> from an unjuſt <hi>definitive Sentence,</hi> or an <hi>unjuſt Grievance</hi> upon an <hi>Interlocutory Decree,</hi> to the next <hi>Superiour
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98452:19"/>Court,</hi> and from thence to the next, and at laſt to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Court at Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the Reformation of <hi>England,</hi> it was juſt to cut off <hi>Appeals to Rome,</hi> (being a Forreign Juriſdiction;) otherwiſe the old <hi>Law of England</hi> was kept to.</p>
            <p>It was therefore Enacted and ordained by the Stat. 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.12. That Appeals ſhould be made from the <hi>Arch-deacon's Court</hi> to the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s; from the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s or his <hi>Commiſſaries,</hi> to the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi>'s Court, or <hi>Arches:</hi> And by the Stat. 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.19. from the <hi>Arches,</hi> to the <hi>King's Majeſty in the High Lourt of Chancery.</hi> This is vulgarly called the <hi>Delegates,</hi> becauſe upon Petition, the <hi>Cord Chancellour</hi> doth <hi>delegate</hi> ſome <hi>Common-Lawyers,</hi> and ſome <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Canon Lawyers,</hi> to hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>This (ſaith the Stat. 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.12.) ſhall be done <hi>by any of the King's Subjects,</hi> and <hi>Reſiants</hi> without any Limitation, except of time, for which the Statute mentioneth 15 Days after the pronouncing the Sentence.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon therefore as any <hi>definitive Sentence,</hi> or any <hi>Interlocutory De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> is given or made, it will be the Party's Wiſdom, to ſend to ſome <hi>Proctor</hi> in the Court, to which his next <hi>Appeal</hi> lyeth, to enter an <hi>Appeal</hi> for him, and to ſend him an <hi>Inhibition,</hi> and <hi>Monition, and</hi> (if <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> hath been denounced againſt him) an <hi>Abſolution.</hi> The <hi>Inhibition</hi> forbids the <hi>Inferiour Judge</hi> to proceed till the <hi>Appeal</hi> be determined; if he diſobeyeth, the Party ſending to his <hi>Proctor,</hi> ſhall have an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication</hi> againſt him. The <hi>Monition</hi> is to admoniſh the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> to ſend up to that <hi>Superiour Court,</hi> by ſuch a time, all the Proceedings in the Caſe. If he diſobeyeth, upon complaint, an <hi>Excommunication</hi> ſhall be ſent down againſt him.</p>
            <p>There is a Practice of the Officers of Superiour Courts, ſometimes upon <hi>Caveats</hi> entered by <hi>Proſecutors,</hi> ſometimes without, to deny the Subject the Liberty ſettled upon him, by the Stat. 24. <hi>H.</hi> 8.12. refuſing to admit his <hi>Appeal,</hi> until he hath <hi>ſworn,</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribed Conformity,</hi> according to the 98 <hi>Canon,</hi> made 1603. The Caſe ſtands thus:</p>
            <p>By the Stat. 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.19. (which was after that for Appeals 24 <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 8.12.) it was enacted, <hi>That the Clergy ſhould not preſume to make any new Canons, or put the ſame in uſe, unleſs they might have the Kings Aſſent firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It is not ſaid, <hi>The Royal Aſſent, and Licence of the King, his Heir and Succeſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98452:20"/> 2. Nor is it ſaid, <hi>Whether there muſt be an Aſſent to the particular put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Execution of each Canon, or a whole lump of them in groſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Nor is it ſaid, his <hi>Aſſent</hi> in or out of <hi>Parliament,</hi> which hath made Queſtions amongſt <hi>Lawyers,</hi> Whether any <hi>Canons</hi> made ſince that time, be of force yea or no? eſpecially conſidering the <hi>Stat.</hi> made 13. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. for <hi>reſtoring the Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction,</hi> taken away by Stat. 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Since that time we have had <hi>Canons</hi> made 1603, and <hi>Anno</hi> 1640, which laſt are in Terms left out, as not confirmed by the Stat. 13. <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>For the others there have been the former <hi>Doubts</hi> raiſed; I ſhall leave them to <hi>Lawyers</hi> to determine; but the Doubt riſeth by the Phraſe uſed in the King's <hi>Aſſent</hi> prefixed to thoſe <hi>Canons</hi> 1603, — <hi>as far as lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being Members of the Church, it may concern them.</hi> And again, <hi>Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Form of a certain Statute made on that behalf,</hi> 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. He who hath a mind to read ſomething <hi>Lawyers</hi> have ſaid upon this Point, may read Mr. <hi>Maynard's Argument</hi> againſt the <hi>Canons,</hi> made 1640. Some of the Heads of which he may find in Dr. <hi>Fuller's Church Hiſtory,</hi> relating to that Year. But certain it is, that Stat. 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.19. ſaith,
<q>
                  <hi>Provided alwayes, That no Canons, Conſtitution, or Ordinance, ſhall be made or put in Execution within this Realm, by Authority of the Convocation of the Clergy, which ſhall be contrariant or repugnant to the King's Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Royal, or the Cuſtoms, Laws, or Statutes of this Realm, any thing contained in this Act to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So that be the Validity of <hi>Canons</hi> made by the <hi>Convocation,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the <hi>King's Aſſent</hi> out of Parliament, as it will, by force of that <hi>Act,</hi> yet no <hi>Canon</hi> can be of <hi>force, contrariant or repugnant to the Laws,</hi> or <hi>Statutes</hi> of the <hi>Realm.</hi> Now the <hi>Stat.</hi> 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.12. was at that time a Statute of the <hi>Realm,</hi> and had given <hi>any of his Majeſties Subjects and Reſiants</hi> a <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Appeal,</hi> without any <hi>Reſtriction</hi> or <hi>Limitation,</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept as to time) or <hi>Qualification</hi> whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Four ſcore Years after this, the Convocation 1. <hi>Jacobi,</hi> makes a body of <hi>Canons;</hi> the 98 of which is in theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Foraſmuch as they who break the Laws, cannot claim any Benefit or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection by the ſame;</hi> (By the way then, all the King's Subjects are Out-Laws.) <hi>We decree and appoint, That after any Judge Eccleſiaſtical hath proceeded judicially againſt obſtinate and factious perſons, and Contemners
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98452:20"/>of Ceremonies, for not obſerving the Rites, and Ceremonies of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>no Judge</hi> ad quem, <hi>ſhall admit, or allow, any his, or their Appeals, unleſs, he having firſt ſeen the Original Appeal, the Party Appealant do firſt promiſe and avow, That he will faithfully keep and obſerve all the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>and alſo the preſcript Form of Common Prayer: and do alſo ſubſcribe to the three Articles, former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by us ſpecified and declared.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Queſtion is, Whether this <hi>Canon</hi> be not made void, and not to be put in Execution by the <hi>Proviſo</hi> before mentioned in the Stat. 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.19?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Statute</hi> makes <hi>Appealing</hi> the Liberty of any of the <hi>King's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Reſiants</hi> without any <hi>Reſtriction</hi> or <hi>Qualification.</hi> The <hi>Canon</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains this, and decrees, The <hi>Appeals</hi> of none but ſuch or ſuch ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Nor can the Validity of the <hi>Canon</hi> with the <hi>King's Aſſent</hi> be pleaded; for the <hi>Proviſo</hi> ſaith, <hi>any thing in this Act to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding;</hi> nor doth the King confirm the <hi>Canon,</hi> but according to this Statute, and ſo far as <hi>lawful, may concern his Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not remember that this Caſe hath been tried; but were it my own concern, I do think, that I ſhould upon a Refuſal to admit my <hi>Appeal,</hi> either preſently <hi>appeal</hi> to the King in his <hi>High Court of Chancery,</hi> that is, to the <hi>Delegates,</hi> or elſe complain in ſome of his <hi>Majeſties's Courts</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that my <hi>Appeal</hi> was refuſed contrary to the Stature 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.12. and hear the Opinions of the Judges about it; for this Practice is a meer <hi>Artifice</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y up the Subject to the pleaſure of a <hi>ſingle Arbitrary Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is all I know can be done to avoid an <hi>Excommunication,</hi> and I dare not promiſe my <hi>Reader,</hi> but that notwithſtanding this, he may be <hi>excommunicated:</hi> for, beſides that this is the great Prize they wait for, and ſo take all Advantages they think they have, to wound one with this Thunder-bolt; there is nothing more ordinary then for <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Surrogates</hi> in thoſe Courts to go on, notwithſtanding <hi>Prohibitions</hi> and <hi>Appeals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing therefore which I have to do, is, to inform my <hi>Reader</hi> what Courſe he may take, if he be impriſoned upon the Writ <hi>de Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municato capiendo,</hi> to get out of Priſon.</p>
            <p>He muſt know no <hi>Prohibition</hi> nor <hi>Inhibition</hi> will ſerve him in that Caſe: not the firſt, becauſe no <hi>Prohibition</hi> will lye againſt the <hi>King's Writ.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Prohibition</hi> is to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who hath done his utmoſt, and hath no more to do in the Caſe, till be come to ſignify for the <hi>Delivery of the Perſon;</hi> and for the ſame Reaſon, an <hi>Appeal</hi> and an <hi>Inhibition</hi> will do
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98452:21"/>him no good; for no <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court</hi> ſhall controul the <hi>King's Writ.</hi> No <hi>Writs</hi> of <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> or <hi>de Homine replegiando,</hi> will help him, nor any Indictment upon <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> becauſe tho the Perſon be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned <hi>per judicium parium,</hi> upon the Verdict of a <hi>Jury,</hi> yet he is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned <hi>per Legem Terrae,</hi> according to the <hi>Common Law of England</hi> They are therefore ill adviſed, who ſeek Deliverance any of theſe ways, and they only augment their own Charge.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Cozens</hi> (who I think was in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time <hi>Dean of the Archers</hi>) in his <hi>Apology for ſome Proceedings in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> tells us, He could never learn more than two ways, by which a Perſon ſo impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned could deliver himſelf. The firſt is, <hi>by Submiſſion to the Biſhop,</hi> and giving him <hi>Caution</hi> by <hi>Bond,</hi> by <hi>Pledg,</hi> or by <hi>Oath,</hi> that <hi>for the time to come he will be obedient to the Commands of the Church in Form of Law.</hi> The <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> is, In caſe <hi>the Party appealeth to a Superiour Court Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> He might have reckoned many more of the ſame nature with the ſecond, which ſuppoſeth the <hi>Court</hi> from whence the <hi>Excommunication</hi> proceeded, to have proceeded wrongfully: In which caſe there are ſeveral <hi>Remedies,</hi> according to the various Errors committed in the Proceedings: I will mention ſome of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If the Party impriſoned, hath brought a Prohibition, by which the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Court hath been commanded to proceed no further, and to abſolve the Perſon if excommunicated, and the Judg hath diſobeyed the Writ, and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and procured the Party to be impriſoned, the Perſon that is impriſoned</hi> at any time in <hi>Term,</hi> upon a <hi>motion,</hi> ſhall have firſt an <hi>Attachment</hi> againſt the <hi>Judg,</hi> and then a Writ of <hi>Superſedeas</hi> to the <hi>Sheriff,</hi> to deliver the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to follow the <hi>Attachment,</hi> without any Submiſſion to the Biſhop at all, or any <hi>Caution.</hi> Such a Writ may be found in the Regiſter of <hi>Original Writs,</hi> p. 66. Nay, if the <hi>Attachment</hi> be granted, and the Perſon be <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned,</hi> or a Writ out, commanding him to be taken, and the Term be done before the <hi>Attachment</hi> can be ſerved, the <hi>Regiſter</hi> tells us, that he ſhall have the ſame Writ during the <hi>Vacation</hi> out of <hi>Chancery:</hi> Nay, it is the Opinion of Men skilled in the Law, that he ſhall have ſuch a <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> upon <hi>Affidavit</hi> made, that the Proceedings are contrary to a <hi>Prohibition</hi> ſerved upon the <hi>Judg,</hi> tho no ſuch <hi>Attachment</hi> be taken out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If the Party impriſoned, or againſt whom the Writ is to take him, tho he be not taken, hath appealed according to the Statute</hi> 24. Hen. 8.12. <hi>if he bringeth into the Court of Chancery an authentick Copy of his Appeal, he ſhall have a Writ of Superſedeas to ſtop the Sheriff from apprehending him, or to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him if he be apprehended,</hi> only this muſt be within a Year after his <hi>Appeal,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:98452:21"/>that it may appear to the Court he hath not deſerted his <hi>Appeal;</hi> you may find Forms of ſuch a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> alſo in the <hi>Regiſter</hi> of <hi>Original Writs;</hi> both theſe are founded upon excellent Reaſon. The Law of <hi>England</hi> will not ſuffer <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judges,</hi> either to invade their Right, or to exalt themſelves againſt their Authority; nor yet ſuffer <hi>Inferiour Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtical Courts</hi> to invade the <hi>Right, Power, and Authority of Superiour Courts</hi> in their own order.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>If a Perſon be ſued in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts for a matter not within their Juriſdiction, and they have caught him upon Contempt, in not appearing or not obeying their Sentence:</hi> Upon a Suggeſtion to the King's Courts, if it appear to them that the <hi>Original Matter</hi> was not cognoſcible in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> they will <hi>ſuperſede</hi> the Proceedings, and order the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned Perſon to be diſcharged.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>If the impriſoned Perſon, or he againſt whom the Writ is out, tho he be not taken, bring a Copy of the Biſhops Significavit into the Courts at Weſtminſter,</hi> and make it appear to the Judges there, that the <hi>cauſe of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> is not therein expreſſed, together <hi>with the day</hi> when it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced; if he be not ſaid to be excommunicated <hi>majori Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione;</hi> if it be not <hi>ſigned by the Biſhop,</hi> or ſaid to be done <hi>Authoritate noſtra ordinarta. If the Party excommunicated be not expreſſed by Name,</hi> the Court will deliver the Perſon. Dr. <hi>Cozens</hi> mentions three of theſe Caſes; and the Reader alſo may find them in the <hi>Regiſter of Writs.</hi> The firſt he ſaith he cannot find in the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> viz. <hi>That the Articles, or matter of the Libel muſt be expreſſed:</hi> nor indeed do I find it there, but it is in ſeveral <hi>Reports.</hi> The Reaſons are, 1. Becauſe the Law will not ſuffer Men to be impriſoned for every light Offence (this Dr. <hi>Cozens</hi> gives.) 2. The ſecond is, becauſe the King's Courts can receive <hi>Significavits</hi> from none but the Perſon to whom (if need be) they may write to diſcharge the Priſoner: Nor will the Court ſuffer a Perſon to be excommunicated, and lye in Priſon for a Crime which the Eccleſiaſtical Court hath no Judgment in; nor yet unleſs it appeareth to the Court, he hath ſtood forty days <hi>excommunicated.</hi> Again, heretofore whole Cities and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities have been <hi>excommunicated,</hi> therefore the Perſon muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Name, or he ſhall not lye there.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let him procure the Copy of the Writ <hi>de Excommunicate capiendo,</hi> and obſerve, 1. If it be iſſued in <hi>Term-time.</hi> 2. <hi>If there were full twenty days betwixt the Teſt</hi> and the <hi>Return.</hi> 3. <hi>If it be made returnable the next Term.</hi> 4. <hi>If there be due Additions in it.</hi> 5. <hi>If before it was delivered to the Sheriff it were entred upon Record in the King's Bench and made returnable into that Court.</hi> All theſe things are required by the <hi>Statute</hi> 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 23. If
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98452:22"/>any of theſe Errors be found, he ſhall upon motion in the King's Bench be diſcharged, and the Writ will be declared <hi>Illegal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, If he can be delivered by none of theſe ways, he may at any ſealing in the <hi>Chancery,</hi> whether it be in <hi>Term</hi> or out of <hi>Term,</hi> upon a Petition to, or <hi>Motion</hi> before the <hi>Lord Chancellour,</hi> have the Writ, <hi>De Cautione admittenda</hi> granted him (in caſe he hath before offered the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop a Bond of 10 or 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> with Sureties <hi>ſtare &amp; parere mandatis Eccleſiae in forma Juris.</hi>) When he hath it, let him by ſome <hi>Attorny,</hi> or <hi>Attorny's Clerk</hi> ſend it, and tender a Bond and ſufficient Sureties with it to the Biſhop, and demand the diſcharge of the <hi>Priſoner:</hi> If it be not preſently done, let him certify ſo much, and at the next Seal move for a ſecond Writ to the Biſhop: Or (which it may be is more adviſable) let him move for a ſecond Writ to the <hi>Sheriff</hi> (the Form of it is in the <hi>Regiſter.</hi>) In that the King commandeth the <hi>Sheriff</hi> to admoniſh the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to accept the <hi>Caution,</hi> and to deliver the <hi>Priſoner,</hi> and further commands him, that in caſe he doth it not in his Preſence, the Sheriff ſhould do it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. If the <hi>Sheriff</hi> yields not <hi>Obedience</hi> upon another Motion, he ought to have a Writ to the <hi>Coroners,</hi> commanding them to take Security of the Sheriff to appear at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> ſuch a day, to ſhew Reaſon why he hath contemned the <hi>King's Writ,</hi> and further it commandeth the <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> to take the Caution of the <hi>Priſoner,</hi> and to deliver him. The <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> may find all this in the <hi>Regiſter</hi> where are the <hi>Forms</hi> of all theſe Writs, and alſo in Dr. <hi>Cozens</hi> his <hi>Apology,</hi> p. 1. c. 2. who being himſelf a Judg in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> cannot be preſumed to have told us any thing but what is <hi>Law,</hi> contrary to their own Intereſt.</p>
            <p>It is true, the Biſhop upon taking ſuch <hi>cautionary Bonds,</hi> doth ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily inſiſt upon the Perſons paying the Proſecutors Charges, but it is unreaſonable,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, becauſe he hath nothing to to do but to <hi>execute the Command of the Writ,</hi> which ſpeaks not a word of Charges.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Becauſe if the <hi>Charges be legally due, the Promoter muſt have alſo a legal way to recover them;</hi> if not, it is <hi>Extortion</hi> for the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judg</hi> to exact them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Becauſe it is no ſufficient return to the King's Writ,</hi> which mentioneth no ſuch thing, to ſay, He could not diſcharge the Priſoner, becauſe he would not pay the Promoters Charge.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the <hi>Legal Charges</hi> are ſmall, uſually the <hi>Priſoner</hi> for his Liberty will pay the Charges: Which are as follow.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98452:22"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <abbr>
                           <hi>s.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <abbr>
                           <hi>d.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the Adverſary's Proctor, every Court-day untill he was excommunicated, and that day when the <hi>Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavit</hi> was decreed: For every day.</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>01</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the Proctor's Procuratory Letter, Seal and Wax.</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>01</cell>
                     <cell>08</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For certifying the Service of the Citation.</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>06</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the Articles, if there were any.</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>05</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For an Act of Court, for every day.</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>02</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the <hi>Significavit.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>05</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the <hi>Significavit</hi> to deliver the Priſoner.</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>05</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the Excommunication and the Schedule.</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>02</cell>
                     <cell>04</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the Writ <hi>de Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> and the Charge of entring it upon Record in the King's Bench, about</cell>
                     <cell>01</cell>
                     <cell>01</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>02</cell>
                     <cell>01</cell>
                     <cell>08</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>If the buſineſs hath proceeded no further then a Libel and Articles, this is all the legal Charges; but if it hath proceeded further, there may be for the Copy of the Anſwer</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>09</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For every Witneſs examined 1 <abbr>
                           <hi>s.</hi>
                        </abbr> and for the firſt</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>01</cell>
                     <cell>06</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For a Fee to the Proctor at Inform.</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>03</cell>
                     <cell>04</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For a definitive Sentence</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>06</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the Advocate at the Sentence</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>But for this the Table of Fees muſt be ſearched; for the Charges are more or leſs, as the Cauſe went further or leſſer way before the <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the beſt Advice I can give to Perſons thus moleſted. Only in the general, I ſhould adviſe any ſuch Perſons theſe two or three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be careful to appear every Court-day in ſome hour when the Court ſitteth, and to take Witneſſes of his being there.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſee as much as he can with his own Eyes, and hear with his own Ears, and act by himſelf as much as he can: For, 1. He cannot expect any other ſhould attend his Cauſe ſo well as himſelf. 2. If any thing be to be done for his Relief in the Civil Courts, he cannot expect any Proctor in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, who is ſworn to do nothing to the prejudice of their own Juriſdiction, ſhould be hearty in the menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or profecution of it. 3. He cannot expect another ſhould be ſo faithful to him to keep his Secrets, as himſelf will be to himſelf. 4. He ſaveth by it all his own Charges.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To be very careful after every Court, to take out from the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter a Copy of the Act or Acts of Court done in his Cauſe (the Regiſter
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98452:23"/>is bound to give him them) and to obſerve if the Regiſter hath faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully entred both his Appearance that day, and what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ded.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To pay the Regiſter, and all other Officers, and ſtrictly according to the <hi>Table of Fees.</hi> It is <hi>Extortion</hi> for them to take more, and by the 135 and 136 <hi>Canons,</hi> the <hi>Regiſter</hi> and <hi>Proctors</hi> are to be ſuſpended ſix Months if they take any thing more.</p>
            <p>The only <hi>Objection</hi> againſt Perſons doing this, is, That they are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their <hi>Forms,</hi> and therefore muſt have a <hi>Proctor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That I never liked the Juſtice I have ſeen diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in thoſe Courts, ſo well, as to inſtruct any in the <hi>Offenſive,</hi> but only in the <hi>Defenſive part:</hi> As to that a little of Form is enough. The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is cited, and Articles delivered to him; when he comes to give his Anſwer, he only ſaith, <hi>The perſonal Anſwer of</hi> R. B. <hi>to the Articles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibited and admitted in this Court againſt him, at the Promotion of</hi> S. T.</p>
            <p>To the firſt he ſaith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo as to the reſt, and concludes with a deſire of the Juſtice of the Court to diſmiſs him.</p>
            <p>After the Anſwer, and the adverſe party hath deſired a time to be ſet to prove the Articles, he hath nothing to do, but to deſire that he might make uſe of the ſame time to produce his Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>If he hath a mind to put in <hi>Interrogatories,</hi> either to croſs examine his Adverſaries Witneſſes, or to examine his own by; he hath nothing to do but to put into the Court, ſuch <hi>Interrogatories</hi> as he ſhall deſire to have propounded, which the Regiſter is bound to take, and to examine the Witneſſes according to them.</p>
            <p>Indeed if he puts in <hi>Exceptions</hi> to the Court, there is a little Form to be obſerved, and ſo alſo in the drawing up the <hi>abſolutory Sentence</hi> to tender to the <hi>Judg</hi> when he comes to give <hi>Sentence.</hi> As to both which I ſhall ſubjoyn Forms, becauſe it may be ſuch <hi>Clerks</hi> or <hi>Attornies at Law</hi> as the Perſon may make uſe of, may not be ſo well acquainted with them.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form for Exceptions.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exceptiones exhibitae die in Anno in quodam Negotia inter partem promoventem, &amp; partem Ream in Curiâ,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quo die</hi> A. B. <hi>pars rea animo excipiendi in Scriptis, &amp; magni ſpecifice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Teſtes omnes, &amp; ſingulos, ex parte productos, juratos, &amp; examinatos, ac contra corum reſpectiva dicta &amp; depoſitiones alias in genere in hoc Negotio, apud acta cum Proteſtatione libertatis ſibi reſervatae, &amp; reſervandae exhibendi Exceptiones alias meliores, &amp; Efficaciores viâ, mado, &amp; juris formâ debitâ qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus melius aut efficacius, de jure poterit, vel poteſt, debuerit, vel etiam debet
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98452:23"/>probare quae propoſuit necnon ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m qualemcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>is effectu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> exind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quevis modo ſecuturum posthac allegandi dicet, allegat ut in his Scriptis, tam genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter quam ſpecialiter proponit prout ſequitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Imprimis, <hi>Quod nulla fide ſaltem de jure ſufficiens, aut valida fuit aut eſt adhibenda pretenſis dictis, aut depoſitionibus teſtium praedictorum pretenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>num ex parte</hi> A. B. <hi>ſuper aelis ſuis peruſis hac in parte redditis, habitis, aut factis pro co, ac ex co quod predicti pretenſi teſtes, &amp; corum quilibet &amp; alter fuerunt, &amp; ſunt in quam plurimis partibus, dictorum ac depoſitionum fuarum predictarum. Falſi vani loqui, varii, vacillantes, ſingulares, inter ſe diſcrepartes, fibi ipſis contrarii &amp; repugnantes, ac in quamplurimis partibus aliis depoſitionum ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum praedictarum inſtructi, informati, &amp; concordes, ſuum quaſi &amp; cundem Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem premeditatum, uniformiter invicem preferentes, dicentes &amp; teſtificantes, cum cauſas ſcientiarum ſuarum pretenſarum, &amp; praedictarum nullo modo legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè, ac ſufficienter reddant, de auditis vero ſolùm &amp; credulitate teſtificantes, &amp; etiam quam plurima teſtificantes, de ſcientiâ ſuâ ut pretendunt propriâ de rebus non in Articulos deductis, prout ex ſerie depoſitionum praedictarum pretenſarum in hac parte utcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> redditarum habitarum, &amp; factarum minifeſte li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, &amp; apparet; &amp; ponit, &amp; excipit tam in genere quam in ſpecie, contra teſtes praedictos &amp; pretenſos conjunctim, ac diviſim &amp; de quolibet particulari.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Imprimis, <hi>Quod nulla fides ſaltem de jure ſufficiens ac valida fuit aut eſt adhibenda dictis &amp; depoſitionibus peruſis praedictorum Teſtium pretenſarum, ex parte</hi> A. B. <hi>in hoc negotio productorum Juratorùm &amp; Examinatorum, pro eo &amp; ex co, quod quidam</hi> R. S. <hi>teſtis pretenſus in hoc negotio utcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ex parte</hi> A. B. <hi>productus, juratus, &amp; examinatus falſe, injuſtè corrupte &amp; contra rei verizatem depoſuit, prout in dictis ſive depoſitionibus fuis pretenſis (hubitâ ad cus relatione) conſtat, liquet &amp; apparet.</hi> — Then repeat his <hi>Depoſition</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and what you have to object, and can by two Witneſſes prove againſt it.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Keep the ſame form as to all other Witneſſes, againſt which you can make any Exceptions, and prove them by two Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>It is good to deliver into the Court your <hi>Exceptions</hi> thus drawn, firſt <hi>generally,</hi> then <hi>particularly.</hi> For tho you muſt prove particularly, yet you may forget ſome Particulars, which notwithſtanding you may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and have proved by virtue of your general Exception, if it cometh within the compaſs of what you aſſert in that: If it be refuſed, you may <hi>appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Make a ſpecial Obſervation, if your Adverſaries Witneſſes have in their Depoſitions ſwore what was not laid in the Articles; for all that cometh to nothing, it being a Rule in their Law, <hi>Quicquid deponitur ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Articulum, deponitur extra Legem;</hi> that is, Whatſoever is depoſed that is not laid in the Articles, is depoſed contrary to the Law. And it is a good ground of <hi>Appeal</hi> for any <hi>Judg Eccleſiaſtical</hi> to take notice of any ſuch thing.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:98452:24"/>
            <p> There are but two caſes more, in which he who is upon the defenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part, will ſtand in need of any of their Forms: That is, 1. In caſe he hath an occaſion during the proceſs of the Buſineſs to put in an <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation:</hi> Or, 2. He may need a <hi>Form</hi> of an <hi>Abſolutory Sentence,</hi> when the Judg comes to give Sentence, becauſe it is the faſhion in thoſe Courts, when the Judg is about to give Sentence, for each Party by himſelf or by his Proctor, to tender to the Judg an <hi>Abſolutory</hi> Sentence for himſelf.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Allegation</hi> may be offered the Judg any time, before the Cauſe be cloſed, but beſt before <hi>Publication</hi> be made of the <hi>Depoſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>matter of it</hi> may be any thing that may help him in his Cauſe. As now, Suppoſe one proſecuted in thoſe Courts for not receiving the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament at Eaſter:</hi> if he can by two Witneſſes prove, that at that time he was many Miles from home, or <hi>ſick</hi> and unable to go out; or that he hath already been puniſhed for it in another Court, he may put any of theſe things in an <hi>Allegation;</hi> the Form of which follows.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>Die anno Domini</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quo die</hi> A. R. <hi>omnibus melioribus viâ &amp; modo &amp; juris forma, ac ad omnem quemcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> juris effectum, exinde quovis modo ſequi valentem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>dicit, allegat, &amp; in his ſcriptis in jure proponit articulatim prout ſequitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Imprimis,</hi> That the ſaid <hi>R. B.</hi> at <hi>Eaſter</hi> laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> upon the day of <hi>April,</hi> &amp;c. and for ſeveral days both before and after the ſaid day, was in the City of <hi>London,</hi> at forty Miles diſtance from his Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then and there attending his lawful occaſions, and ſo could not receive the Sacrament in his Pariſh-Church of <hi>A.</hi> aforeſaid.</item>
                     <item>2. That this is a juſt and legal Excuſe, which ought to be allowed in this Court for his not being that day at his Pariſh-Church, and hearing divine Service, and receiving the Sacrament.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quae omnia praedict.</hi> R. <hi>paratus eſt probare in formâ juris, ſicut huic Curiae viſum fuerit decernere.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The like may be as to any other ſpecial matter which he hath to alledg, ſetting his hand to the <hi>Allegation,</hi> and delivering it into the Judg of the Court, or his Surrogate. He may give his Allegation by word of mouth, but it is better to do it in Writing before Witneſs.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form of an <hi>Abſolutory Sentence.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Dei nomine Amen. Auditis, viſis ac intellectis, plenarie, &amp; mature diſcuſſis per nos</hi> N. D. <hi>legum. Doctorem, Curiae officialem, principaliter, ritè &amp; legitimè conſtitutum meritis, &amp; circumſtantiis cujuſdam negotii correctionis ſive officii promotionis, quod corum nobis in judicio extitit inter</hi> R. N. <hi>partem pretenſam hujuſmodi negotium promoventem, ex unâ, &amp;</hi> S. R. <hi>noſtrâ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> juriſdictionis, partem contra quam hujuſmodi negotium promovetur, ex alterâ quod vertitur, &amp; pendet indeciſum, rite &amp; legitime procedentibus praedictis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98452:24"/>praedictis per corum reſpective procuratores</hi> [if they uſe no <hi>Proctors,</hi> it muſt be <hi>propriis perſonis] in judicio legit. comparentes, parte<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> praefati</hi> S. T. <hi>Sententiam ferri, &amp; juſtitiam fieri pro parte ſuâ parte vero praefati</hi> R. N. <hi>fieri, pro parte ſuâ inſtanter, reſpectivè poſtulante, &amp; petente rimato<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> penitus per nos, ac diligenter recenſito toto, &amp; integro proceſſu in hujuſmodi negotio, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis, &amp; factis, ſervatiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> per nos de jure hac in parte ſervandis ad noſtrae ſententiae abſolutorum ſive finalis Decreti prolationem in eodem pretenſo negotio ferendo ſic duximus procedendum fore, ac procedimus in hunc qui ſequitur modum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quia peracta inactitata, deducta, exhibita, propoſita, allegata, probata pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; confeſſata comperimus luculenter &amp; invenimus partem prefatam promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventem,</hi> R. N. <hi>intentionem ſuam in quibuſdam Articulis ex parte ſuâ exhibitis quorum dictorum Articulorum Tenor ſequitur, &amp; ſunt. In Nomine Dei Amen. Nos,</hi> &amp;c. Then followeth the recitation of the Articles, <hi>quos aelos pro hic lectos, &amp; inſertos habemus &amp; haberi volumus, nullo modo ſaltem ſufficienter aut legitimè fundâſſe aut prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe, ſed in probatione corundem Articulorum, omnino defeciſſe, &amp; deficere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Idcirco nos,</hi> N. D. <hi>judex antedictus Chriſti Nomine primitus in vocato, ac ipſum ſolum Deum praeponentes, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> de &amp; cum Concilio Juriſperitorum cum quibus hâc in parte communicavimus praefatum</hi> S. T. <hi>ab inſtantiâ &amp; impetitione, praefati</hi> R. N. <hi>quoad praedicta in Articulis pretenſa praedicta, abſolvendum &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendum fore debere pronunciamus, decernimus, &amp; declaramus, prout ipſum</hi> S. T. <hi>ſic dimittimus, &amp; abſolvimus per preſentes; praefatum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> R. N. <hi>in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſis legitimis in hâc parte factis &amp; fiendis eidem</hi> S. T. <hi>ſolvendis inſuper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnamus per hanc ſententiam noſtram abſolutoriam, ſive finale noſtrum decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quam ſive quod ferimus &amp; promulgamus in his ſcriptis Taxationem vero, ſive moderationem expenſarum hujuſmodi, nobis aut alii judici hâc in parte competenti cuicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> reſervandi &amp; reſervamus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>If the Judg give Sentence againſt you, you will be admoniſhed; in that Caſe take the firſt opportunity of entring an <hi>Appeal</hi> in the next <hi>Superiour Eccleſiaſtical Court,</hi> unleſs <hi>Common Lawyers</hi> tell you, your Cauſe is ſuch as a <hi>Prohibition</hi> will lye in, then move for that as ſoon as you can.</p>
            <p>If you have removed your Cauſe into the <hi>Arches,</hi> there are divers Proctors that are learned Men, and faithful to their <hi>Clients,</hi> by whom you muſt there (as alſo in the <hi>Court of Delegates,</hi> if you ſee cauſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from the <hi>Arches</hi> thither) proſecute your Cauſe. To whoſe care I leave you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>
               <hi>The Reader is deſired to paſs by, or amend what Errors have hapened in the Preſs, by reaſon of the Authors abſence.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
